<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The poore's pension: a sermon preached in Gregories Church in Sudbury in the county of Suffolke, May 12. 1643. Upon occasion of the charitable reliefe that yearly then, and there is given, towards the covering or clothing of a hundred poore people, according to the will of the donour M Martine Cole, late of the towne aforesaid deceased. By Samuel Rogers, Master in Arts, and Minister of Much-Tey in Essex. Imprimatur Ja. Cranford, Aug. 12. 1644.</title>
            <author>Rogers, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E10_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859846</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859846</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111946</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 2:E10[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poore's pension: a sermon preached in Gregories Church in Sudbury in the county of Suffolke, May 12. 1643. Upon occasion of the charitable reliefe that yearly then, and there is given, towards the covering or clothing of a hundred poore people, according to the will of the donour M Martine Cole, late of the towne aforesaid deceased. By Samuel Rogers, Master in Arts, and Minister of Much-Tey in Essex. Imprimatur Ja. Cranford, Aug. 12. 1644.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for Edward Brewster at the signe of the Bible on Fleet-bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 23.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job XXXI, 19 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111946:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111946:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Poores Penſion: A SERMON PREACHED IN <hi>GREGORIES</hi> Church in <hi>Sudbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolke, May</hi> 12. 1643.</p>
            <p>Upon occaſion of the charitable reliefe that yearly then, and there is given, towards the covering or clothing of a hundred poore people, according to the will of the Donour M <hi>Martine Cole,</hi> late of the Towne aforeſaid deceaſed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Rogers,</hi> Maſter in Arts, and Miniſter of Much-Tey in ESSEX.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 41.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed is he that conſidereth the poore, the Lord will deliver him in time of trouble.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MARK 14.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ye have the poore with you alwayes, and whenſoever you will, you may doe them good.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Hoc eſt occidere hominem, vitae ſuae ei ſubſidia denegare, eave, ne inter loculos tuos includas ſalutem inopum, tanquam in tumulis ſepelias vitam pauperum.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Amb.</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Si Deorum cultores ſimulacra inſenſibilia excolunt, &amp; quicquid pretioſi habent in ea conferunt, quanto juſtius eſt &amp; verius viventia Dei ſimulacra excolere?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lact. Inſt. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> JA. CRANFORD, <hi>Aug.</hi> 12. 1644.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Edward Brewster</hi> at the Signe of the Bible on Fleet-bridge. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111946:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull the Major and Aldermen, to the reverend the Miniſters, and to the diſcreet Bailiffe and Burgeſſes, with the reſt of the well-affected people of the Town of <hi>Sudbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolke,</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Authour devotes himſelfe, and his ſervice, and dedicates this little parcell of his paines.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sirs, and my much reſpected Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon firſt preached amongſt you, and now dedicated to you, hath had occaſionally it's firſt birth from him, from whom the Author naturally hath had his being, whoſe pains in this kind, and upon this occaſion, had it been afforded, as of right expected, this worthleſſe work of mine might have been well ſpared, but it was his pleaſure to put me upon the worke, and therefore my<note n="*" place="margin">— mihi juſsa capeſſere fas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt.</note> duty to obey him, to whom I owe my ſelfe; this and the ſame that was at first directed to your eares is now made viſible to your eyes; after it had been preached, for above halfe a yeares ſpace it came not once into my thoughts it ſhould be printed, I accounted it no other then as an untimely birth that never ſhould ſee the ſunne; and the reaſon why now I brought it forth to light, was not becauſe of any high conceit, that either I have, or expect you ſhould have of its worth, (I am conſcious to my ſelfe of my owne imbecillity which even herein may be ſeen to others) but in this printing age (wherein are vented all things both new and old, both good and had) for any one that is a Penman, it is expected that he ſhould not onely ſet his tongue a work to ſpeake but alſo his Pen to write; to be altogetho ſilent in this kind, and in theſe dayes may ſeeme a ſolaeciſme; but that was not it which drew this from me. I could well enough have ſtill ſhrouded my ſelfe under the ſhadow of obſcuritie, and would willingly have kept any thing of mine in this kind from publike view, but more forceable arguments did over-power me, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt drawne from the preſsing miſeries of multitudes of people in many places; the objects of pitty which ſhould ſet a worke charity we every where to be ſeen, how many ſhiftleſſe and helpleſſe creatures (whoſe loud cries may he heard even afarre off) doe importune us to put to our helping hands, to
<pb facs="tcp:111946:2"/>doe for them, that are able to doe little or nothing for themſelves, this then may ſerve, as their <hi>Eccho,</hi> to give you (as it were) the rebounding of their voices.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I conſidered the hard-heartedneſſe of moſt in moſt places, theſe are the times wherein (I thinke) never greater neceſſity, and yet (I feare) never leſſe charitie, and no wonder that in this iron age men have ſuch hard hearts, for it was foretold by our Saviour that in theſe laſt dayes<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 24.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhould abound, and the love of many ſhould waxe cold,<note n="d" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.18.</note> whereby we know it is the laſt time, for never more vanity, and never leſſe charity,<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 5.4.</note> the cries of the diſtreſſed and oppreſſed that doe pierce the eares of God even in the higheſt Heaven, cannot enter into the eares, or at leaſt the hearts of men on earth. Who is not more or leſſe wanting in making a ſupply to the wants of others? in whoſe hearts doe the kindled coales of love appeare ſo violent at to breake forth into a vehement flame? are not moſt men herein ſtarke cold, and doe not the beſt ſeeme to be but lukewarme? needs there not then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to quicken us, a ſpurre to provoke us? make uſe then of this for that purpoſe, at leaſt let it be as a remembrancer to minde us of our duty, which ſometimes we ſhall be ready peradventure willingly to forget.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, concerning this particular occaſion which firſt put theſe words into my mouth, the ſame was the cauſe why I let them fall from my pen, for I underſtood that notwithſtanding you have had many Sermons, two yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon this occaſion, yet not one appeares extant, they were (it ſeemes, no longer lived then the breath wherein they were delivered; whereupon I thought with my ſelfe that ſomething in this kind were better then nothing to be kept upon record in honour and for memoriall of that great good worke of charity, which the Apoſtle ſaies is a never failing grace, <hi>1 Cor. 13.8.</hi> of that kind (it ſeemes) was this, for the laſt will of the deceaſed is as a laſting deed, to inſure your poore of their yearely reliefe for ever: that this therefore was a good worke, none that is good can deny, for it is of good uſe tending to the good of many, and that it was alſo a great good work, I think it may well be ſo ſaid to be, in that I feare me it will not be greatly followed, when and by whom amongst you will it be ſeconded? Now good workes especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of this nature are ſo rare, that they may well be welcommed when they doe appeare, and certainly the perpetuity of that work (were there no other cauſe) deſerves the continuance of this, your poore's yearely Penſion may well be honoured with an annuall celebration; ſee then how one good work is ſeconded with another, a bodily almes for the poore is recompenced with a ſpirituall benefit for all; you have (it ſeemes) uſually on this day, upon
<pb facs="tcp:111946:3"/>this occaſion a double Sermon, and why may not each be of double uſe? <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, for Commemoration of what is done for the time paſt; for the Lord will ſo grace good workes, that they ſhall be (as it were) a ſurviving iſſue; Saint <hi>John</hi> tels us what he heard God from heaven ſay, <hi>Rev. 14.13.</hi> Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, both in that they reſt from their labours, as alſo in that their works doe follow them, nay let me adde, they are bleſſed in that their works doe ſtill ſurvive them to, for they follow after them to Heaven to be rewarded, and yet they remaine ſtill behind them on earth to be renowned. <hi>Prov. 10.7. The memory of the juſt is bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, for Exhortation to what ſhould be done for time to come: For ſo (as it ſeemes) was it the mind of this Donour that each Minister of your two Pariſhes ſhould be requeſted yearely on this day to make an Exhortation to the people, and if they doe it not themſelves, to cauſe it to be done by ſome others, and hath allowed them a recompence: Now whereto ſerves an Exhortation but to move us unto, or put us upon the practice or performance of a good work or duty? and then is it of ſo much the greater force, when as it is grounded upon the Examples of others ſet before us, who though they are dead, yet ſpeake unto us, and though not vocally, yet really call upon us, to doe the ſame good workes, that ſo we may be repaid with the ſame rich recompence of reward? For the Examples of good works are as patternes ſet before us to teach us that the ſame or ſuch like ſhould proceed from us; this worke of almes to the poore, you are not ſo much to conſider as done by another, but ſo to reflect upon your ſelves, as hence to learne what herein ſhould be done by you; hence are you exhorted from this example of our brother deceaſed to be of the ſame minde and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; conſidering it is a high point of wiſdome, whilſt we have the things of this life to make the beſt and the moſt of them, which is not when we engroſſe them to our ſelves, but when in conſcience and obedience to God we diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute them to others; the Apoſtle mindes us of what our Saviour ſaies (oh let it appeare that we beleeve it to be a truth) <hi>That it is more bleſſed to give then to receive,</hi> Act. <hi>20.35.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any thing ſpoken this way be here to be found that may ſtirre up com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and acuate affection, that may ſo work upon our hearts as to ſet a worke our hands ſo to extend charity<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 4.27.</note> that we our ſelves may find mercy, it is enough I have my deſired and: Two things more only by way of <hi>Preface</hi> I deſire you would be pleaſed to take notice of, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning the matter which you ſhall here find; Expect no newes, of which every dales plenty and variety doth alwayes fill us, if not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb facs="tcp:111946:3"/>times ſurfet us, and were our newes as true and good, as riſe and common, there would ſeeme to be no want; newes is now growne ſo ſtale, that for any thing not new to come forth may ſeeme to be newes indeed,<note place="margin">Nihil dictum quod non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum prius.</note> no other newes have you here, for the wiſe man ſaies,<note n="*" place="margin">Ecc. 1.9, 10.</note> there is no new thing under the ſun, is there any thing whereof it may be ſaid, See this is new? it hath been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of old time which was before us: I ſhould be loth to be cenſured by you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly, as the Apoſtle was by the Athenians moſt unjuſtly to be a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Act. 17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</note> babler for bringing new and ſtrange doctrine to your eares; or that you ſhould be accounted (as they were, and did appeare ſo to be) ſo addicted to novelty, that the truths of God ſhould ſeeme ſtrange to you; Here you ſhall find com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things, which are therefore never the<note n="*" place="margin">Omnia bona communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va, quo commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niora eo melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</note> worſe, or of never the leſſe uſe, common they are indeed, becauſe they concerne all; ſuch things that you have formerly (and it may be often heard) and yet are now againe hereby put in mind of, that ſo you let them not<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 2.1.</note> ſtip; It is not amiſſe<note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.12.</note> to put you alwaies in remembrance of theſe things, though ye know them, that you may be eſtabliſhed in the truth:<note n="*" place="margin">Nunquam ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis dicitur, quod nunquam ſatis diſcitur, <hi>Sen. epiſt. 27.</hi>
               </note> that is never enough ſpoken, that is never too well learned, nor can be too much practiſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, concerning the manner of delivery both at first and now, it is without excellency of ſpeech; affected eloquence in preaching is not<note n="*" place="margin">Venerabiles &amp; verè Deo digni Apoſtoli. Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cum eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in omnibus puritate vita, &amp; animi vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibus clarij non magni pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debont ſermonis ornatum. <hi>Euſeb. lib. 3. cap. 24.</hi>
               </note> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique, for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.18.</note> moſt learned (as may be thought) of all the rest tels us expreſly that when he was ſent of Chriſt to preach, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ranne thus in theſe words,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.17.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>&amp;c. and I confeſſe, my opinion is that plaine ſpeaking is as commendable in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as plaine dealing is neceſſary in trading, as Miniſters therefore preſſe this upon people, ſo are they to practiſe that themſelves, chooſing rather to profit people with wholeſome doctrine, then to pleaſe them with delightſome Phraſes; this that you have here at firſt, ſhewed it ſelfe in a plaine dreſſe, and ſince, had I neither liſt nor leiſure to put it into another habit, had I skill to doe it, who can now in theſe ſad times apply himſelfe to the ſtudie of witty inventions; or delight others with the curioſity of nice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions? <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith thus of Rhetoricke, <hi>Pacis eſt comes, ottique ſocia, &amp; jam bene conſtitutae reipublicae velut alumna quaedam eloquentia;</hi> which if ſo, how unſeaſonable is it at this time for us, and what little uſe have we now to make thereof: except to worke the more upon our affections, the more pathetically to expreſſe our bitter lamentations? our wits may well be dull'd, when as our hearts cannot but be<note n="*" place="margin">Lam. 1.20.</note> bemudded with our trouble.</p>
            <p>Again, had I had will, yet could I not have time to doe herein as I would, for theſe impoliſhed meditations I let paſſe out of my hands with as much
<pb facs="tcp:111946:4"/>haſte as they came into my minde; all I could doe was but to review them, I could not refine them; for all the time I had to make them legible and fit for the Preſſe, was ſurreptitiouſly taken away from my other imployments, now and then a little, which little being ſoone miſſed, I could not then ſpare much, or more; I muſt needs therefore implore your kind acceptance of this my weake conception, which wanting its due perfection through the want of the midwifery of time hath come to an immature and untimely birth; ſuch as it was, it is, and ſuch as it is, it is freely yours, if you pleaſe but to take it as your owne; if any thing herein be amiſſe, I cannot but take it to my ſelfe; <hi>Humanum eſt errare,</hi> it is incident to mans nature to erre, and whatſoever is good I dare not but aſcribe it to God, <hi>Omne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſupernè,</hi> Every thing that good is, is from above: Now the God of all glory enrich our hearts ſo with his grace, that we may be fruitfull in repentance and obedience to him, and abounding in love and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, and endue us with a greater meaſure of wiſdome, not of this world, which is<note place="margin">Jam. 3.15, 27.</note> earthly, ſenſuall, and divelliſh, but of that from above, which is pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be entreated, full of mercy, and good fruits, without partiality and without hypocriſie, that we may enjoy the fruit of righteouſneſſe which is peace, to all them that worke righteouſneſſe, and that make peace, which is the Prayer of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>An unworthy Miniſter of the Goſpell, and your ſervant in the worke of the Lord, SAMUEL ROGERS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111946:4"/>
            <head>The Poores Penſion.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOB. 31.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If I have ſeene any periſh for want of clothing, or any poore without covering.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are ſpoken by that holy man <hi>Job</hi> in his owne defence, who being falſly accuſed by his friends is inforced to juſtifie himſelfe, he pleads innocency whiles they reproach him with iniquity, and takes God to witneſſe his integritie, notwithſtanding they condemne him with hypocriſie; and in this Chapter doth he accurſe himſelfe with many a heavie execration, if he were guilty of ſuch hainous offences that he doth there mention: <hi>e. g.</hi> if I have walked with vanity, or if my foot hath haſted to deceit; Let me be weighed in an even ballance, &amp;c. <hi>verſes</hi> 5, 6. if my ſtep hath turned out of the way, and mine heart hath walked after mine eyes, and if any blot hath cleaved to my hands, then let me ſow, and let another eat; yea, let my off-ſpring be rooted out, &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8. and ſo ſtill goeth on in the following verſes clearing of himſelfe, and amongſt other things (as being none of the leaſt ſinnes) he acquits himſelfe of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the poore, which may be done not onely in doing them wrong, but no leſſe in not doing them right, therefore ſaith he, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. <hi>If I have with-held the poore from their deſire, or have cauſed the eyes of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111946:5"/>widow to faile: Or have eaten my morſell alone, and the fatherleſſe hath not eaten thereof: If I have ſeen any periſh for want of clothing, or any poore without covering: If his loynes have not bleſſed me, and if he were not warmed with the fleece of my ſheep: If I have lift up my hand againſt the fatherleſſe, when I ſaw my helpe in the gate: Then let mine arine fall from my ſhoulder-blade, and mine arme be broken from the bone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words of the Text may be taken two wayes: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Either Abſolutely, conſidered in themſelves as an entire Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without any connexion or dependance, then may they be thus read, <hi>If I have ſeen any periſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i.e.</hi> I have not ſeen any to periſh, this is an ordinary phraſe and common ſpeech in Scripture to expreſſe a manifeſt negation by way of ſuppoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Parts: </seg>
               </label> Or Relatively, <hi>i. e.</hi> as having relation to, or dependance upon the following words, and as they are ſo conſidered, we have here</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A Suppoſition, <hi>i.e.</hi> the thing ſuppoſed as falſe and wicked; <hi>If I have ſeen</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i.e.</hi> were it ſo that I ſhould ſuffer any to periſh for want, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Inference, what followes thereupon, <hi>i.e.</hi> what doth he then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſhould happen, a heavie curſe to lighten; <hi>Then let mine arme fall from my ſhoulder-blade, and mine arme be broken from the bone.</hi> verſ. 22. as if he ſhould ſay, were I herein guilty, then doe I wiſh that this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould befall me.</p>
            <p>This one Suppoſition may afford us theſe three ſeverall Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Whilſt we are here in this world we may ſometimes happen to be in great want.</hi> This is implyed in the words, that there are and may be ſuch as are ready to periſh for want of clothing, and thoſe ſo poore, that they may be even without covering.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>We are to ſee to, that is, provide for thoſe that are in want, and that ſtand in great need of helpe.</hi> This is alſo implyed in the words, in that he doth accurſe himſelfe, if he had been wanting this way, if he had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered any to periſh for want of clothing, or the poore to be without covering.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>We are not to ſuffer any to periſh in extreme need for want of neceſſary reliefe:</hi> For herein doth <hi>Job</hi> juſtifie himſelfe, that he had not been ſo hard-hearted as to ſuffer any to periſh for want of clothing; and had he ſo done, he doth adjudge himſelfe worthy of exemplary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Theſe are the chiefe points conſiderable in the words, of each in their order.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111946:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whilſt we are here in this world we may fall into want;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>and come to be in great need.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This cannot greatly be doubted of, but will eaſily be condeſcended to, for were it not out of queſtion, multitudes of witneſſes might be produced, and by daily experience it might be proved. How many are there upon our owne knowledge that experimentally find this to be a truth? nay, who is there that can aſſure or ſecure himſelfe, that he for his part ſhall be none of thoſe that ſhall make it good? <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> peradventure the richeſt, I am ſure the wiſeſt of meere men, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was in leaſt danger of want, yet by his wiſedome he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that his riches could not keep him from want, therefore ſaith he, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.11. <hi>I returned, and ſaw under the Sunne, that the race is not to the ſwift, nor the battell to the ſtrong, neither yet bread to the wiſe, nor yet riches to men of underſtanding, nor yet favour to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all.</hi> There is none whoever that can promiſe himſelfe the attainment or enjoyment of any outward comfort or contentment, no not ſo much as of food and raiment, it is not mans wit or wiſdome that can get it, but only a divine providence that doth give it: the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. doth give in charge concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning rich men, that are moſt free from want, that they be not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, for they may fall into want, though therefore they beare up their heads aloft, they may come downe as low as others, they may not then truſt in uncertaine riches, and why? becauſe uncertaine, and that both in reſpect none is ſure to partake of them, as alſo none is certaine of the continuance of them, for even when we have them, we are not ſure of them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Riches certainly make themſelves wings, and ſly away,</hi> ſo that while we are looking on them, they are paſſing from us; and <hi>Chap.</hi> 27 <hi>ver.</hi> 24. <hi>Riches</hi> (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>are not for ever, neither doth the crowne endure to all generations;</hi> the world it ſelfe is ſubject to mutation, and therefore the things of the world cannot be limited to ſucceſſion; ſo that for all theſe things, there is none but may be bred in want, or brought to want. — <hi>Pauper ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> jacet,</hi> ſtore of poore in every place. But what doe I ſpeake of men? when as Chriſt the Sonne of God, and the heire of the world,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.</note> had no better entertainment whilſt he lived in the world, then to ſuffer the want both of food (for we reade of him that he was both hungry and thirſty) and of lodging,<note place="margin">Matth. 21.18. Joh. 19.28.</note> he had not where to lay his head, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.58. The Apoſtles alſo after Chriſt met with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111946:6"/>the ſame meaſure that did Chriſt their Lord and Maſter, ſo ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4. he was in neceſſities and diſtreſſes, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. he was poore, although he made many rich; he had nothing, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he poſſeſſed him, who is in ſtead of all things; ſo he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>In wearineſſe and painfulneſſe, in watchings of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in hunger and thirſt, in faſtings often, in cold and nakedneſſe,</hi> and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Even unto this preſent houre we both hunger and thirſt, and are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and are buffetted, and have no certaine dwelling place;</hi> in ſo much that he was faine to work for his living, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. And labour, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with our hands, and 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.8. he ſaies that he wrought with labour and travaile night and day; but let me not runne too farre in a beaten path, I might even looſe my ſelfe in a multitude of Examples of this kind, to returne therefore homeward to our text, <hi>Job</hi> that ſpeaking theſe words gives us occaſion to note this truth, may ſerve as an example in ſtead of all,<note place="margin">Job 1.3.</note> he that did <hi>affluere opibus,</hi> abound in all things, came to be <hi>vix in pelle quidem,</hi> ſcarce had he any thing about him,<note place="margin">2.7.</note> no not a whole skin left him, he that before ſuffered not any to periſh for want of clothing, was now himſelfe ſo poore, that he was without covering; ſo that from him comes the Proverbe at this day in uſe,<note place="margin">His Codrus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitò qui modò Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſus crat.</note> 
               <hi>As poore as Job.</hi> And this was not his caſe alone thus to come to want, but hath been the condition of moſt of the beſt of Gods people, even of thoſe of whom the world was not worthy, for it is ſaid of them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37, 38. that <hi>they wandered about in ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skins, and goat-skins, in deſerts, and in mountaines, in dens, and in caves of the earth, being deſtitute, afflicted, and tormented:</hi> ſo that if not from our owne experience, yet from the examples of others we muſt needs be driven to confeſſe, that whilſt we live in this world we may come to be in great want; nay, let me further adde, there is none in the world but is in want; I ſhould adjudges it to be proudly and preſumptuouſly ſpoken of any amongſt us that ſhould ſay they were ſo rich and encreaſed with goods,<note place="margin">Revel. 3.17.</note> that they had need of nothing, for as long as we live in this world we are and ſhall be one way or other in want,<note place="margin">How we may be ſaid to be in want.</note> and of ſomething or other we ſhall ſtand in need; we may be in want any of theſe three wayes, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If we want what we need to have; <hi>viz.</hi> the comforts and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of life, without which none can at leaſt long ſubſiſt, this is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judgement threatned to the rebellious and diſobedient, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.48. yea, not ſeldome it fals out to be the portion of Gods owne people,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111946:6"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13. the Apoſtle laies it downe as a duty; that we ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute to the neceſſity of Saints, ſo that even Saints may be in ſo great neceſſity as to ſtand in need of reliefe, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.41-48. our Saviour there tels us that the wicked at the laſt day ſhall be indited and arraigned, caſt, and condemned, for not relieving Chriſt in his members, ſo that it doth there appeare, that even thoſe who are ſo deare to Chriſt that their caſe he accounts as his own, may neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in this world be in a needy condition, <hi>viz.</hi> hungry, thirſty, ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, naked, ſick and in priſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. Famine and nakedneſſe are in the catalogue of thoſe many evils which befall not only the worſt of men, but the beſt that live; and by ſo much are theſe in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter want, by how much they are deſtitute of thoſe things that can leaſt be ſpared, this is the diſconſolate condition of thouſands of poore people in the Chriſtian world, nay, to come neater to our own bone and fleſh, how many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland</hi> have ſuffered the extremity of this want, how many ſad reports from thence have for this long time fill'd our eares, I would I might have ſaid alſo, our hearts? have we not lately heard how that multitudes of them are expoſed to ſtarving and cold, the unavoidable executioners of death? yea are there not many in moſt places of this land, whom the devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſword (that doth make havock and ſpoile) hath brought to as bad a ſtay? Oh that we had a fellow-feeling of the miſeries of our fellow-brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> We are in want, when we want what we deſire to have, though we have ſo much as God ſees it to be enough, and others thinke too much; yet if we would have more, we then are ſtill in want, and thus truly few but are in great want; yea, though they have great abundance, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.7. <hi>There is that maketh himſelfe rich, and yet hath nothing,</hi> would be accounted better men then they are, theſe are vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious boaſters, and <hi>there is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that maketh himſelfe poore, and yet hath great riches,</hi> though very rich, yet ſtill complaine that they are but poore, becauſe they are not contented with what they have, and theſe are covetous perſons, who even choake themſelves with greedineſſe, whoſe hearts deſires ſeeme as large as * hell it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Prov. 27.20.</note> their eies are never ſatisfied with ſeeing, much leſſe their hearts with deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; like as a man in a dropſie, doth ſtill deſire drinke, and the more he poures downe, the more thirſty he is, the nature of the diſeaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as cauſeth him to drinke much more then would doe him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111946:7"/>good; or like a ravening Maſtiffe that ſtands ſtaring at the tables end greedily gaping for a morſell, which he hath no ſooner ſwallowed downe and devoured, but he as eagerly lookes for as much more, as if he had had nothing at all; or like other hungry hounds, who being at a loſſe, goe about bawling after their prey, ſo it is with theſe, they goe about all the day long with this <hi>Quaere</hi> in their mouthes,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>who will ſhew us any good? i.e.</hi> a good Farme, a good penni-worth, a good bargaine, good ready money, &amp;c. the goods of this world they can never have enough of, whenas a little or nothing of ſpirituall good contents them; and wonder not that I compare theſe men (though men) to dogs, for the Scripture doth the ſame, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.14, 15. And at Evening<note n="*" place="margin">Prophetando non optando dicit, ut apparet <hi>ver. 6.</hi>
               </note> let them returne, <hi>i.e.</hi> they will ſo doe according to their wonted manner, and make a noiſe like a dogge, and goe round about the citie, and wander up and downe for meat, and grudge if they be not ſatisfied. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.15.<note n="*" place="margin">Has filias ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit lunius eſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nudiuts bi ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam linguam ſargun em in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſi entèr ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentem &amp; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>ntem; Annot. in loc.</note> 
               <hi>The horſe-leach hath two daughters, crying, Give, give;</hi> and the world hath two ſonnes to match with thoſe two daughters, the rich miſer, and the miſerable poore, both crying Give, give; the one cries give, becauſe he hath nothing, and therefore in want; and the other as greedily cries give, becauſe he is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with any thing, and ſo ſtill in want; and therefore may he well be reckoned there among thoſe things which are never ſatisfied, and which ſay not, <hi>It is enough:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it amor nammi, quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ip a pecunia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſcu</note> for the more he hath, the more ſtill doth he deſire to have, Enough is a language which he can by no meanes learne, neither will he reſt content till his mouth is ſtopt up with dirt, and then<note n="*" place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templ. 8. part.</note> leſſe then two ells of earth ſhall ſerve him, whom for ſmall part of the curſe inflicted upon worldlings as a juſt judgement of God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.10. <hi>He that loveth ſilver, ſhall not be ſatisfied with ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; nor he that loveth abundance, with increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>We are in want, when we want what we ought to have.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a man hath never ſo much, yet if he hath not that he ſhould have, for all he hath, he is ſtill nevertheleſſe in want. <hi>e.g.</hi> if a man have maſſes of wealth, even<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 73.7.</note> more then heart could wiſh, yet if he hath not heart and grace to make good uſe of what he hath, he is in greateſt want, better have nothing, then to be never the better for any thing, and indeed he that hath not wherewithall to make good uſe of what he hath, hath as good as nothing; <hi>What ſhall it profit a man</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>if he ſhall gaine the whole world, and loſe his ownt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111946:7"/>ſoule, Mark</hi> 8.36. ſo that were it poſſible that a man might have the command of the whole world, yet for all that might he be in want of that that ſhould ſave his ſoule, and ſo never the nearer, or the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; how many are there thus in want, and yet are not ſenſible of their wants? like as <hi>Martha</hi> who was much troubled about theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, that nothing might be wanting, yet our Saviour doth diſcover that there was want, and tels her that there was in her wanting of the chiefe thing, the only thing needfull which ſhe took not good notice of, <hi>Luke</hi> 10 42. and thus are we not all in want of thoſe things that we ought to have, and abound in, <hi>viz.</hi> in thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, contentedneſſe, holy obedience and heavenly wiſdome to make the beſt of theſe earthly bleſſings? <hi>There is an evill</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 6.1, 2.) <hi>Which I have ſeene under the Sunne, and it is common among men. A man to whom God hath given riches, wealth and honour, ſo that he wanteth nothing for his ſoule of all that he deſireth, yet God giveth him not power to eate thereof, &amp;c.</hi> though he might ſeeme to want nothing, yet he wants the chiefe thing, even a ſanctified heart, which is the gift of God that ſhould make good all things.</p>
            <p>And who now is there living in this world that in one (if not more) of theſe three reſpects may not be ſaid to be in want; is it not a plaine caſe who doubts of it, but that whilſt we live here we may happen to be in great want? and why doth the Lord in his wiſdome ſee good to ſuffer us or any, at any time to be in want, ſeeing he is able to give to every one a fulneſſe? For theſe reaſons, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> To weane us from the world; for if we had our fulneſſe here, we would be loth away hence, we would make this our thorow-fare to be our reſting place, if all things here ſhould be according to our hearts deſire, and we ſhould never be in want of any thing, we would never care for Heaven, but (like<note n="*" place="margin">Mark 9.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> on Mount Tabor when he wiſt not what he ſaid,) we would be ready to ſay, <hi>It is good for us-to be here:</hi> let us therefore never looke any further, but here pitch our tabernacles, this appeares in that notwithſtanding whiles we do live in this world we live in a world of miſery, and cannot wholly free or ſecure our ſelves from want, yet how prone are we to ſeeke for true felicitie in earthly proſperity; and when it comes to, how loth are we and the world to part, but how much more unwilling ſhould we then be, if we might have even what we would? but therefore ſhall we, yea, the beſt that are, ſometimes be in want, that ſo we may
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111946:8"/>minde homeward more, like the Prodigall ſonne, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.13.19. who ſo long as he had his fill, mindes not his home, but no ſooner began he to be in want, but then he longs after his fathers houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To humble us and keepe us downe, ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> tels the people that the Lord to humble them ſuffered them to hunger, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.3. for if ſo be we ſhould be free from all wants, we ſhould not know our ſelves, nor yet our God, therefore <hi>Agur</hi> wiſely deſires the meane, as being the only ſafe condition, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8. <hi>Give me neither povertie nor riches, feed me with food convenient for me:</hi> and why? becauſe in either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes there is danger, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Leſt I be full, and denie thee, and ſay Who is the Lord? or leſt I be poore, and ſteale, and take the Name of my God in vaine;</hi> ſo that a fulneſſe in this world makes us in danger to ſwell againſt God; the Lord therefore oft-times will make us fare hard, and keep us upon ſhort commons, leſt we ſhould grow fat, and waxe wanton: and ſo caſt off and forſake God, as the Lord complaines that the people for whom he had done ſo much, ſerved him after all. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.15. <hi>But Jeſurun waxed fat and kicked: Thou art waxen fat, thou art growen thicke, thou art covered with fatneſſe: then he forſooke God which made him, and lightly esteemed the rocke of his ſalvation.</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>Of the Rock that begate thee thou art unmindfull, and haſt forgotten God that formed thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Becauſe the Lord hereby gives us to underſtand that the things of this life are not according to our will, but are at his owne diſpoſe, that it is he that giveth them, or elſe we cannot have them, he alſo continueth them, or elſe we cannot keep them, that we are not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and independant creatures, but are continually at his finding and keeping, that it is not our fore-caſt to get, nor our care to keepe that can doe either, but the wiſdome and providence of God that doth order and diſpoſe of all to whom, and as it ſeemes good to him; <hi>Which of you</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>by taking thought can adde one cubit to his ſtature. Mat.</hi> 6.27. It is God that made the world (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) and all things therein, that is the Lord of Heaven and earth, that needeth not any thing, who giveth to all life and breath, and all things, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.24, 25. and <hi>Deut</hi> 8.3. <hi>He humbled and ſuffered thee to hunger,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that he might make thee know, that man doth not live by bread only but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lord doth man live:</hi> it is not the outward meanes that we doe live upon, but Gods bleſſing upon the mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es that we live by; and <hi>verſes</hi> 17, 18.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111946:8"/>Leſt <hi>thou ſay in thy heart, My power, and the might of mine hand hath gotten me this wealth. But thou ſhalt remember the Lord thy God: for it is he that giveth thee power to get this wealth, &amp;c.</hi> ſo the wiſe man tels us, that riches and wealth with power to partake thereof, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the uſe thereof, is the gift of God, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.19. this, God would have us to know, and therefore doth he give and take away at his pleaſure, thus dealt he with <hi>Job,</hi> which made him to acknowledge the ſame, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.21. <hi>The Lord gave</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and the Lord hath taken away,</hi> &amp;c. The Lord ſometimes will let us want, that thereby we may ſee what ſhiftleſſe creatures we are, and what an all-ſufficient God he is.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Hence may we ſee the little cauſe that we have to be ſo in love with this world, or with the things of this life, all which cannot keep or ſecure us from want, therefore ſo often called vanities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are vaine things to truſt to, or doate upon, they cannot profit nor deliver, and therefore vaine, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.21. and great reaſon why we ſhould be moſt deſirous of, and moſt carefull to provide for the happineſſe of the world to come, looke never to be well till we get thither, but ever, either to be in want of ſomething, or at leaſt ſubject to the want of all things; but if after this time of our pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage we get once ſafe home to Heaven, then feare no want of any thing that may make the creature happie, for there is a fulneſſe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, <hi>In thy preſence, O God, is fulneſſe of joy, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for evermore, Pſal</hi> 16.11. the vaſt deſires of thy heart which cannot now be ſatisfied, ſhall then be fill'd brim full and running over. <hi>How excellent is thy loving kindneſſe, O God</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the children of men put their trust under the ſhadow of thy wings, they ſhall be abundantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thy Houſe,</hi> (by houſe here may be underſtood not only the place of grace, <hi>i.e.</hi> where the Lord doth afford the meanes of grace, where he doth diſpenſe his holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, ſpirituall dainties and delicacies which the Lord himſelfe hath provided for the nouriſhing and cheriſhing of the ſoules of his people in this life, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25.6. but alſo the palace of glory, <hi>i.e.</hi> the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of Heaven, provided for the Saints of God after this life, which is alſo called the Houſe of God, <hi>Job.</hi> 14.2. where there is an everlaſting well-ſpring of joy that can never be exhauſted or drawne dry) <hi>and thou ſhalt make them drinke of the river of thy pleaſures, for with thee is the fountaine of life, and in thy light ſhall we ſee light:</hi> the very
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111946:9"/>thoughts whereof even now cannot but raviſh thy heart, haſt thou any comfortable hopes hereof? thou canſt not then but breake forth into admiration and ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Oh how great is thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which thou haſt laid up for them that feare thee! Pſal.</hi> 31.19. who would be willing to lie ſtill in a dungeon almoſt halfe ſtarved, or at the beſt where he hath but enough to keep life and ſoule together, and not deſire rather inlargement to goe to his owne home, where he may have even what he will? this conſideration, to wit, of the miſery of this life, and the happineſſe of that to come made the Saints of God in all ages ſo willing to die, and ſo loth to live as the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs,<note n="*" place="margin">Ieb. 11.23, 16.</note> 
               <hi>all which died in faith not having received the promiſes: i. e.</hi> as touching the land of Canaan (which although it was the land of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, yet was it to them as a ſtrange countrey, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9.) but having ſeene them afarre off, and were perſwaded of them, and embraced them, <hi>i.e.</hi> through faith did they ſee and beleeve that in many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to come, theſe Promiſes made to them ſhould be made good to their poſterity, but for their owne parts they confeſſed that they were ſtrangers and pilgrimes on the earth, and why? becauſe they deſired a better countrey, that is an heavenly, where they might to the full enjoy their God, who hath prepared for them that City.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> This may ſerve to condemne the madneſſe and folly of worldlings that carpe and care, moile and toile, to ſcrape together and hoard up earthly goods, thinking thereby to keep them and theirs from want, whenas alas this is not the way, for all that thou canſt doe, thou maiſt fall into want,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 127.2.</note> 
               <hi>It is in vaine for thee to riſe up early, to ſit up late, and to eate the bread of ſorrowes,</hi> it is Gods bleſſing only that can doe thee good, for if thou ſhouldſt ſwelt thy heart, thou canſt not keep thy ſelf from want, yea, though thou makeſt thy ſelfe never ſo great a drudge whilſt thou liveſt here, thou ſhalt be in want in one kinde or other; ſee then and conſider how thou doſt play the foole, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.8. <hi>There is one alone, and there is not a ſecond</hi> (a covetous man is a ſingular foole, he hath ſcarce his fellow, and wherein doth his folly appeare? in that though) <hi>he hath neither child nor brother:</hi> (none that he can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure himſelfe ſhall be his heire) <hi>yet is there no end of all his labour, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is his eye ſatisfied with riches, neither ſaith he, For whom doe I labour and bereave my ſoule of good? this is alſo vanity, yea it is a ſore travell.</hi> The Text is ſo plaine and to purpoſe, that I ſhall not need to comment upon it.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111946:9"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Take we notice that the want of good things is not ſimply in it ſelfe an evill thing, for if ſo, the Lord would never ſuffer any of his to fall into want; and yet theſe are thoſe that uſually in this life are in greateſt want of theſe outward things, whenas the wicked for the moſt part enjoy them in farre greater abundance, we ſee it here in Gods dealing with <hi>Job,</hi> who was ſtript of all, and yet ſuch an one of whom God gives this teſtimony, <hi>viz.</hi> that there was none like him in the earth; <hi>a perfect and an upright man, one that feared God and eſchewed evill,</hi> Chap. 1.8. and it was not his caſe alone, for, for the moſt part they are the<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 2.5.</note> poore of this world that are the choſen of God, a great comfort therefore it may be to the godly poore in time of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt want, that for all this the Lord loves them nevertheleſſe; and that want is not evill, but good for them, otherwiſe it ſhould not be their portion, for the Lord doth not with-hold good things from them, becauſe he could not beteame them on them: but becauſe he ſees they are not good for them, but that the want of them is better; yea, beſt for them, and this are they to be aſſured of, and to reſt ſatisfied with, for theſe outward things the Lord often gives them to the wicked in wrath, and with-holds them from his in love.</p>
            <p>But hath not the Lord promiſed that there ſhall be <hi>no want to them that feare him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9. and that <hi>no good thing will he with-hold from them that walk uprightly? Pſal.</hi> 84.11.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Resp. </seg>1</label> There ſhall be no want to ſuch, <hi>i.e.</hi> of any good thing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.10. ſo that thou being ſuch an one to whom the Promiſe is made, if any thing be wanting to thee, thou maiſt be ſure it is not good for thee, and then better that thou doſt want it, then if thou didſt enjoy it: what wiſe man will complaine of that want which if he had would prove more hurtfull then gainfull to him?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>No good thing will God with-hold,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore not wants, which to them are alſo good things,<note place="margin">Wants good to the Godly, and how.</note> as doth appeare in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the preſent: becauſe the leſſe thou haſt, the leſſe haſt thou to give an account of; Poverty is a light burden, and a great advantage to us in the way to Heaven; whereas the wealthy are ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Hab. 2.6.</note> laden <hi>with thick clay,</hi> and ſo ſhackled with fetters of ſilver, and chaines of gold, that they come on heavily and ſtaggeringly, and oft-times fall ſhort;<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 13.22.</note> the cares of this world, and the deceitfulneſſe of riches are heavie clogs at mens heeles, which make many that they cannot once ſtirre,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111946:10"/>nor take one right ſtep in the way to Heaven, hence comes it to paſſe that it's ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 19.23.</note> hard for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of God: <hi>For they that will be rich,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9.) <hi>fall into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts, which drowne men in deſtruction and perdition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This advantage have the poore over the rich, that their path-way to Heaven lies more plaine, and ſmooth, and is not beſet with ſo many thornes and briers, they may therefore paſſe on with a more ſwift pace. A ſhip of great burthen, and heavie laden comes with great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and difficulty, and with much adoe is brought in; but a light pinnace comes a long ſwiftly, and is brought in with much eaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> For the future: for thy wants doe but make roome for, and make thee fit for a rich ſupply: <hi>for the needy ſhall not alway be forgotten, the expectation of the poore ſhall not periſh for ever, Pſal.</hi> 9.18. <hi>My God ſhall ſupply all your need</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.19.) <hi>according to his riches in glory by Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> if there be in God and in Chriſt enough (thou thinkſt) to ſatisfie the deſires of thy heart, feare not but thou ſhalt have enough.</p>
            <p>See then how good it is for Gods people (at leaſt ſometimes) to be in want, and yet how afraid are the very beſt of falling into outward wants, as if they thought themſelves wiſer then God that knowes what is beſt and fitteſt for them: ſenſe indeed cannot credit it, but faith muſt beleeve it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> Are not we falne into want? (though while we live here we ſhall never be wholly free, yet have we great abundance over many others) Oh what great cauſe have we then to bleſſe God, and how carefull ſhould we be to ſerve this good God<note n="*" place="margin">4 Tim. 6.17.</note> that giveth us all good things richly to enjoy: <hi>When thou haſt eaten, and art full</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>then thou ſhalt bleſſe the Lord thy God, for the good land which he hath given thee. Beware that thou forget not the Lord thy God, in not keeping his Commandements, and his judgements, and his ſtatutes which I command thee this day: Deut.</hi> 8.10, 11. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The more to move us hereto conſider what are we above others? we altogether undeſerving creatures,<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 32.10.</note> unworthy of the leaſt of all his mercies, deſerve not the crummes that fall from his table, that the Lord then ſhould deale better with us then with others our betters; that he ſhould let them want, and yet let us abound, that he ſhould cut them ſhort, and yet give us our fill; we can give no other reaſon but Gods meere mercy to us above
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111946:10"/>others, ſeeing he might have dealt with us in this kind as with others, yea, worſe then with any, ſeeing that there is none, no not the richeſt and greateſt in the world, but might have been as little and low as the pooreſt and meaneſt on earth,<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath made thee to differ?</hi> haſt thou not cauſe to ſay with <hi>David, Who am I, O Lord God, and what is my houſe, that thou haſt brought me hitherto?</hi> 2 Sam. 7.18.</p>
            <p>Againe conſider, <hi>Where much is given, there will be much required:</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48. this is held but equitable amongſt men, and therefore as juſt with God; whenas God doth more for us then for others, he in juſtice expects more of us then of others, the more coſt the more fruit, others that have not ſo much as we, have not ſo much to anſwer for as we; and the more God hath beſtowed upon thee, the greater is thy debt of thankfulneſſe, and the greater thy duty of obedience.</p>
            <p>Doe we ſee others in want? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>5</label> Oh how ready ſhould we be to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them a ſupply, reach forth our helping hands, and doe for them even as for our ſelves, conſidering that as it might have beene, ſo we know not how ſoon it may be thus with us; the ſame argument doth the Apoſtle uſe as a motive, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Remember them that are in bonds as bound with them, and them which ſuffer adverſity, as being your ſelves alſo in the body;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, it ſtands you in hand to relieve thoſe in want, in regard it may be ſaid to be in ſome reſpect a<note n="*" place="margin">Respecta poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitatis, licèt non certitudini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon caſe, yea, it might be thy caſe, put thy ſelfe therefore into their condition, that is by laying it to heart, as if it were thine owne, and then be hard-hearted and ſtrait-handed if thou canſt: but of this now but by the way, and more at large in the next points.</p>
            <p>Would we not fall into want? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>6</label> the beſt preſervatives that I can afford you to keep you out of the danger thereof are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Means to keep from want:</note>
            </p>
            <p>Make God thy portion: as did <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.57. and then thou haſt enough, as he ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.1. <hi>The Lord is my ſhepherd,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>I ſhall not want:</hi> doſt thou thinke God (<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50.12.</note> whoſe is the world, and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof) is able to ſupply thy wants, if then thou doſt enjoy this God, how canſt thou feare any want? the Lord made himſelfe known to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Pilgrim, even<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 7.5.</note> when he had not a foot of land of his owne to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. not only the Almighty, but alſo the All-ſufficient God, noting God is every way able to doe for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; he hath wherewithall to give to all their fill, the word is very<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſortis.</note> emphaticall, and full of comfort, and <hi>Abraham</hi> made good uſe thereof, as it doth appeare afterwards, for when he was in a great
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111946:11"/>ſtrait he caſts himſelfe upon Gods All-ſufficiencie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> compoſit i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ex <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> relativo, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, &amp; ſic idem ſignificat quod Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſibi vel per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſufficient. Vel (ut alii vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riva u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> mamma, quia nutrit Deut fi lios ſuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cum omnia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um affluentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſicut nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rix in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> papiliis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>genie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will provide, Gen.</hi> 22.8. and <hi>Jehovah-jireh</hi> (God will ſee to, and provide for his) <hi>ver.</hi> 14. may well be the motto of all true beleevers, the children of faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Solus habet omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> habet ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnia</note> if thou haſt God, thou haſt more then all things elſe, for one God will doe thee more good, and ſtand thee more in ſtead, then the whole world beſide, <hi>David</hi> ſaw cauſe why he ſhould rejoyce more in the light of Gods countenance, then the men of the world in the encreaſe of their corne and wine, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6, 7. Get thy heart therefore repleniſhed with him that made the heart, otherwiſe thou wilt alwayes be in want, not the world, but the God of the world can keepe thee from want,<note n="*" place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> avariatiae totus non ſufficit orbis.</note> the whole world is not enough to ſatisfie the greedy deſire of a covetous Cormorant: We reade of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great (who never left coveting and conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring till be had made himſelfe Monarch of the then knowne world, or at leaſt ſo much thereof as was knowne to or heard of by him) that he wept, becauſe there were no more worlds for him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and no wonder that the world is not enough, nay, were there many worlds they would prove all too little to ſatisfie an unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied heart, for a circle can never fit or fill a triangle, now we know the for me of the world is circular, and of mans heart triangular, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible then is it for this to be fill'd with that, it is God only then that in the Trinitie of perſons can ſuite well with, and fill to the full this triangle, mans heart.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Get a right to, and a ſtate in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt;<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 2.16.</note> that thou art his, and he is thine; then all that he hath (who is heire of the world) is alſo thine, ſo farre forth as it is for thy good; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21, 22, 23. <hi>All things are yours: Whether Paul, or Apollo, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things preſent, or things to come, all are yours, And ye are Christs, and Chriſt is Gods.</hi> All the good that God hath that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petible to creatures is derived through Chriſt to us, he therefore that hath Chriſt, hath ſuch a treaſure to enrich him, and ſuch a Magazine of all good things, and that of all ſorts to furniſh him, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for ſuch an one to come to want; <hi>For he that ſpared not his owne Son</hi> (as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.) <hi>but delivered him up for us all: how ſhall he not with him alſo freely give us all things?</hi> if he give us the greater, will he deny us the leſſe? if he beſtowes Chriſt upon us, who is more worth then all things, then ſurely will he not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from us any thing which in compariſon of him is as nothing,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111946:11"/>whenas therefore he gives Chriſt, he gives not a naked Chriſts, but Chriſt with all his benefits, and all his appertenances, <hi>i.e.</hi> all manner of good things, which God gives in over and above the bargaine to all true beleevers: ſo that the having of Chriſt doth<note n="*" place="margin">Omne maju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> includit in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e minus.</note> imply all other things and more, foraſmuch as he is farre better to thee then any thing elſe can be, like as <hi>Elkanah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Am not I bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to thee then ten ſons?</hi> to be ſure, Chriſt is better then ten thouſand worlds; for not only for his ſake doſt thou partake of good things, but alſo in and through him haſt thou the ſanctified uſe of all thoſe things; it was not then without cauſe that that holy Martyr <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> ſtill cried out to the laſt, <hi>None but Chriſt, none but Chriſt;</hi> and that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> accounted all things but as dung that ſo he might win Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Give to thoſe that are in want: this the men of the world will not beleeve to be a meanes to keep from want, but rather to bring to want, therefore when call'd upon to give reliefe, their anſwer is, they muſt ſee what they ſhall have themſelves, they may give what they have away and want, &amp;c. whenas their atheiſticall hearts will not ſuffer them to beleeve, that to give is the way to have: <hi>Give,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>and it ſhall be given unto you, good meaſure, preſſed downe, and ſhaken together, and running over, ſhall men give into your boſome: Luk.</hi> 6.38. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.27. <hi>He that giveth unto the poore, ſhall not lack:</hi> Almes to the poore is like the pouring of a paile of water into a dry pump, that fetcheth up a great deale more; contrariwiſe, any way to wrong the poore, whereby to enrich our ſelves, is the ready way to come to want, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.16. <hi>He that oppreſſeth the poore to increaſe his riches, and he that giveth to the rich, ſhall ſurely come to want.</hi> Yea, it is ſaid, that he that with-holdeth more then is meet ſhall ſurely come to want.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Walke cloſe with God in the way of holy obedience: All Gods Promiſes are conditionall; yea, of theſe outward good things hath he promiſed abundance, but it is upon the condition of obedience, as doth appeare plainly, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.25, 26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. and largely <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.12, 13, 14, 15. and particularly <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.1-14. be not we then wanting in duty to God, and God will not be wanting in any good thing to us, and how can we looke that God ſhould make good his Promiſes if we look not at all to our performances? we make them voide whenas we keep not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111946:12"/>if thou beeſt a true ſervant of God, doe not thinke him to be ſo hard a maſter, as to ſuffer any of his houſhold to want, it is more then ever was heard of or knowne.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.25.</note> Walke before God then, and be upright, and truſt God to provide for thee, follow God in his way, and then art thou in a faire way to have a ſupply of all things, <hi>Seeke firſt</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> in the firſt place as the chiefeſt thing) <hi>the Kingdome of God, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you. Matth.</hi> 6.33. I end this with what the Apoſtle ſaith 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Walke honeſtly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that ye may have lack of nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, Get true contentedneſſe of minde: a contented minde (we ſay) is worth all, and indeed ſo it is, for it will make a ſupply to all thy wants, a little with contentment is enough, that will make us even in povertie ſay<note n="*" place="margin">Itiner. Ser. pa. <hi>465.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Hepheſtion</hi> to <hi>Alexander,</hi> As I had nothing, ſo I wanted nothing; whenas enough without contentment will be too little, this appeares in<note n="*" place="margin">1 K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 21.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab,</hi> who though he was King of Iſrael, yet (as if a Kingdome had been too little) he was not contented, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he might have to himſelfe poore <hi>Naboth's</hi> vineyard, and the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">Plut. Apoph. Regum.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> who hearing of the great riches of India, divided all his Kingdome of Macedonia forthwith among his Captaines and ſouldiers (ſo little content took he in a Kingdome) ſaying he prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the riches of India (hoped for) before all his father <hi>Philip</hi> left him in Macedonia;<note n="*" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hall</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templ. 7. part.</note> ſo that riches and poverty are more in the heart then in the hand, he is wealthy that is contented with a little, and he is poore that is in want with abundance: Every body wants ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, but there is one thing we all want, which if we had more of, we ſhould want nothing, and that is true contentedneſſe; which only with Godlineſſe is great gaine, that reſts well enough ſatisfied onely with the meere neceſſaries of life: if therefore we would have enough of the world, let us labour for more of this grace, and to attaine to ſo great a meaſure thereof as to ſay with the Apoſtle <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>Not that I ſpeake in respect of want, for I have learned in whatſoever ſtate I am therewith to be content: I know both how to be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and I know how to abound, every where, and in all things I am instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, both to be full, and to be hungry, both to abound, and to ſuffer need, &amp;c.</hi> If in thy wants thou canſt learne to be content, thou haſt that then which is better then that thou wanteſt; and the more to move hereto conſider of theſe things:<note place="margin">Conſider.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thou haſt (that haſt leaſt) farre more then thou canſt deſerve;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111946:12"/>alas ſhould God deale with us according to our deſerts, we ſhould not be worth the leaſt mite, when therefore thou art ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of want, compare but thy receits with thy deſerts, and then thou wilt thinke thou haſt enough and ſpeed'ſt wondrous well, for even the worſt condition out of Hell deſerves contentedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thou haſt much more then many others; look not upward with an ambitious eye to thoſe above thee, but with an humble heart downward to thoſe beneath thee, envie not what others have, but lay to heart what others want, and then reflect upon thy ſelfe, and ſee if thou haſt not cauſe to bleſſe God for what thou haſt: doth not God deale better with thee then with thy betters, and canſt thou then find fault?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thou haſt that which is fitteſt for thee: whatſoever thou haſt be it little or much, thou ought'ſt to beleeve to be beſt for thee, and not that which thou thinkeſt to be enough, but that which God knowes to be enough for thee muſt thou be contented with; would it not be accounted folly and childiſhneſſe, for a little man and of ſmall ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to weare apparell though gay and gorgeous of the greateſt and largeſt ſize, ſhould he not rather deſire that that is fitteſt for him, though more plaine and meane? if the child be diſcontented becauſe it may not weare his fathers bootes, or if it cry for the greateſt ſpoone, whenas it hath another that is fitter, is it not for want of wit? ſo doth it appeare that we have not the uſe (at leaſt) of ſanctified rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whenas we reſt not contented with thoſe things that are fitteſt for us, or as if we thought our ſelves wiſer then God, that we were beſt able to judge of the fitneſſe; ſo that all theſe things ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, where is there any cauſe of diſcontent but in our ſelves? wouldſt thou then be contented with a little? get thy mind to think, and thy heart to beleeve that thou haſt enough, and then wilt thou not feare any want, fit thy mind to thy meaſure, and not thy meaſure to thy mind; for that will never be, while the world ſtands, for the mind of man is of larger compaſſe then the whole world; what can more be ſaid concerning this, either to arme us againſt want, or to comfort us in want? I have been ſo over-large in this point, that I muſt be more briefe in what followes; the ſecond point is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is our dutie to ſee to, that is, provide for thoſe that are in want:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>We are to afford help and reliefe to thoſe that are in miſery and diſtreſſe.</hi> Had not <hi>Job</hi> thought this to be his duty, wherefore did he wiſh, if he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111946:13"/>were wanting herein, ſo great a curſe to light upon him as <hi>ver.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>This is commanded by Precept:<note place="margin">Reliefe of the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, 1 Commanded.</note> theſe few places of Scripture in ſtead of many more doe ſufficiently prove it, ſee what is given in charge (and ſo what we are bound to dutie) <hi>Lev.</hi> 25.35. <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.7-11. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.42. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. by grace, there the Apoſtle meanes almes-giving, as doth plainly appeare in the fore-going verſes, and this he calleth the grace of God, as <hi>ver.</hi> 1. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> it is God that worketh in us as in other things, ſo in this thing both to will and to doe of his good pleaſure: and it is not enough (you ſee there) to have ſomething of this grace, but it is expected and required that we abound therein.</p>
            <p>It is alſo highly commended in practice,<note place="margin">2 Commended.</note> the Saints of God in all ages have been much honoured for this their freeneſſe and forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in relieving of their poore brethren: the contribution made by the Macedonians for the poore Saints at Jeruſalem is upon record, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.26. and againe are the ſame Chriſtians highly commended for the ſame thing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. &amp;c. the Apoſtle there doth beare them witneſſe how that when they themſelves were in an afflicted condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and at a pooreſtay, ſo that they ſeemed rather themſelves to want reliefe, then to be able to give reliefe, yet even then they aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their liberalitie, and that they had gathered ſo much that the Apoſtle was loth to receive it of them, he ſeeing it was beyond their power, in ſo much that they prayed him with much entreaty to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thereof, and to diſtribute it among the Saints that were in want. The <hi>Philippians</hi> alſo above all other Churches next to thoſe of Macedonia had the praiſe for communicating more then once to the neceſſities of the Apoſtle, for he ſpeakes it to their commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſince he departed from Macedonia, no other Church beſide theirs had ſent him a ſupply, which he was glad of, not ſo much for his owne benefit, as for their gaine, which ſhould be great in the day of account, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.14.18. the care alſo that the Chriſtians had of the poore in the time of the Apoſtles is ſpoken of <hi>Act.</hi> 11.29, 30. they ſold their lands and goods rather then they would ſuffer their poore brethren to want, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.45. and there were godly and diſcreet of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers (that ſhould not be ciphers) elected by the Church, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Apoſtles purpoſely to overſee and look after thoſe that were in want and ſtood in need of reliefe, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.3, 5. I ſhall not need ſpeake of particular perſons who are greatly renowned in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111946:13"/>Scripture for their hoſptality and almes-deeds, as <hi>Abraham, Lot, David, cornelius</hi> (of whoſe almes there was in the preſence of God a <hi>memorandum</hi> made <hi>Acts</hi> 10.31.) <hi>Dorcas,</hi> (whoſe good workes and almes-deeds were to be ſeen and ſhewed, when ſhe her ſelf was not, the poore could not tell how with patience to take her death, ſhe had done ſo much for them all the time of her life, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.36, 39.) and many more of no ſmall note whom I muſt paſſe over in ſilence; yea, it is worth the obſerving how that our Saviour himſelfe, though he was relieved by others, yet even out of that would he ordinarily give a portion to the<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 13.29.</note> poore, giving us thereby to underſtand that even the poore themſelves ſhould pay collection, that is, part with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what (though the leſſe) to thoſe that are in greater need then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are. And we are to afford reliefe to thoſe that are in need for theſe reaſons: becauſe it is <hi>bonum, juſtum, &amp; honeſtum;</hi> it is a thing good, right, and honeſt ſo to doe, as will thus appeare:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, To give almes is to doe good, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>As we have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie let us doe good to all men</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>especially to them that are of the houſhold of faith:</hi> and verſe 6. it appeares what good he meanes, even the communicating of good things, in which well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing we muſt abound, and not waxe weary, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16. <hi>To doe good, and to communicate, forget not</hi> (ſaith that Authour) wee muſt be free and forward to diſtribute good things, for this is to doe good, and therefore is it our duty, for<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 12.9.</note> we muſt cleave to and follow that that is good; and this is good, and that in ſundry reſpects, good both for giver and receivers, good both for our ſelves, ours, and others.</p>
            <p>Good for others:
<list>
                  <item>1. In that hereby they receive good,<note place="margin">To give Almes good in divers reſpects: <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </note> for their bowels are refreſhed; as the Apoſtle ſaith the Saints were by <hi>Philemon,</hi> ver. 7.</item>
                  <item>2. In that hereby they doe good, (if they have any goodneſſe at all in them,) <hi>viz.</hi> bleſſe us, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and bleſſe God for us.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Good for our ſelves:
<list>
                  <item>1. For the preſent: for <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.27. <hi>He that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to the poore ſhall not lack,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.1, 2. <hi>Him that conſidereth the poore, the Lord will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and keep alive, and he ſhall be bleſſed upon the earth.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>2. For the furture: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for by this meanes thou maiſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111946:14"/>provide well for eternitie; ſo the Apoſtle gives in charge concerning rich men, that they doe good, yea, that they be rich in good works, <hi>viz.</hi> to diſtribute and communicate, laying up in ſtore for themſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternall life, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18, 19. ſo that.</item>
               </list>
not ſo much to lay up, as to lay out is the beſt way to provide for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, therefore doth our Saviour give us that good counſell, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. from the example of the unjuſt ſteward, who was ſo wiſe for himſelfe whilſt he was in office, as that by the liberall giving away of his maſters goods, he might be well provided for afterwards, when he had nothing left him; <hi>And I ſay unto you,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>Make to your ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſſe, that when ye ſaile, they may receive you into everlaſting habitations. For if ye have not been faithfull in the unrighteous Mammon, who will commit to your truſt the true riches?</hi> ver. 11. <hi>q.d.</hi> If ye be untruſty in diſpoſing (according to the will of God) theſe temporall goods, how can ye expect that he ſhould beſtow upon you everlaſting happineſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? and <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.33. <hi>Sell that ye have, and give almes, q.d.</hi> at no hand let the poore want what ſhift ſoever ye make, rather ſell, then want to give; <hi>Provide your ſelves bags, which waxe not old, a treaſure in the heavens that faileth not, where no thiefe approacheth, neither moth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth:</hi> ſo that to disburſe to the poore on earth (in conſcience and obedience to God) is before hand to provide a rich treaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and who that beleeves this would not thinke himſelfe happy in ſuch an exchange? is not this the beſt alchimy to turne earth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven? is not this a good bargaine to part with * vaine and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine things, to partake of reall and durable riches? beleeve it, this is the beſt improvement, and the moſt that can be made of theſe things: whereupon a worthy Father thus exhorts, * <hi>Si vis eſſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator optimus, foenerator egregius, da, quod, non potes retinere, ut recipias quod non poteris amittere, da modicum, ut recipias centuplum, da tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem poſſeſſionem, ut conſequaris haereditatem aeternam:</hi> Wouldſt thou be a good merchant, a great uſurer, give, that thou canſt not keepe, that thou maiſt receive that thou ſhalt not looſe; give (though but) little that thou maiſt receive a hundred fold; give thy earthly goods, that thou maiſt obtaine eternall life: contrary wiſe, if thou ſheweſt no mercy here, expect not to find mercy hereafter; <hi>For he ſhall have judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 1.2.</note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 6.17.</note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. in Ep.</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111946:14"/>
               <hi>without mercy, that hath ſhewed no mercy,</hi> Jam. 2.13. and <hi>who ſo ſtoppeth his eares at the cry of the poore, he alſo ſhall cry himſelfe, but ſhall not be heard.</hi> Prov. 21.13.</p>
            <p>Good for ours; this a meanes to make our poſterity bleſſed; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.26. it is the property of a righteous man to be ever mercifull and lending, and it is ſaid of ſuch an one that <hi>his ſeed is bleſſed</hi> (and that is no ſmall bleſſing) though then thou haſt given much, and as yet haſt received but little, doe not give over, and thinke all is loſt, for if thou ſhouldſt never live to enjoy the crop in this life, there is the more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind for thy children after thee, and how can we poſſibly provide better for them, then to lay up in ſtore Gods bleſſing for them: and that by our meanes they ſhould come to be heires thereof; the good proviſion therefore that we ſhould make for our children conſiſts not ſo much in laying up, as in laying out;<note n="*" place="margin">Quo plures domi ſunt tibi liberi, eò plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tibi non recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum, ſed ero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandum eſt. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. de elee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſ.</hi>
               </note> the more children thou haſt at home, the more muſt thou not hoard up for them, but the more muſt thou give to the poore; a ſtrange paradox to the men of the world, they will never beleeve it, but the faith of a Chriſtian will perſwade him to greater matters then this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> We muſt give reliefe to thoſe that are in want, becauſe it is but juſt and right we ſhould ſo doe, and ſo much as we are wanting in matter of juſtice, and faile in point of equity, we fall ſhort of our duty, for <hi>That which is altogether juſt ſhalt thou follow, that thou maiſt live, and inherit the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi> Deu. 16.20. and that it is ſo, may appeare, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Withhold not good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the power of thine hand to doe it:</hi> obſerve, it is their due from us, therefore our debt to them, and we muſt not deferre payment of this debt. <hi>Say not unto thy neighbour, Goe and come againe, and to morrow I will give, when thou haſt it by thee.</hi> ver. 28. the poore have ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Ius Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, licèt non proprietatis.</note> right to rich mens goods in point of equity, and according to the rule of charitie; though therefore they may be caſt or nonſuited at the Common law of man, yet may the ſue us in the Court of Conſcience, and have judgement againſt us at Gods tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſeat of juſtice, <hi>Beware</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>that there be not a thought in thy wicked heart,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and thine eye be evill againſt thy poore brother, and thou giveſt him nought, and he cry unto the Lord againſt thee, and it be ſin unto thee.</hi> Deut. 15 9.</p>
            <p>The Hebrew Rabbines, and the Jewes at this day call almes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Righteouſneſſe, not only becauſe they ought to be of goods rightly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111946:15"/>got, but alſo becauſe it is but juſt and right that they ſhould be given, and not becauſe they make Righteous (as the<note n="*" place="margin">To whom we may ſay ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their owne Tranſlation, Matt. 6.1. <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te, ne ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiam veſtram faciatis;</hi> ſake heed you make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m not your Juſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion. <hi>Light <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot Miſcell.</hi>
               </note> Papiſts would make us beleeve, who make this to be a chiefe one of their many meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous works) and the wealth of this world is by our Saviour called <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon,</hi> Luke 16.11. and ſo indeed it is, when unjuſtly withheld as well as when not rightly got; ſo that contrary to right and reaſon, to hold faſt that we ought to part with, turnes even well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten goods into the Mammon of unrighteouſneſſe; and why is it a matter of juſtice to give almes? becauſe we are not the abſolute owners, but only the<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 16.2.</note> ſtewards of Gods gifts, now it is<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3.</note> required of a ſteward that he be found faithfull as well in his disburſements as in his receits, not to engroſſe all to himſelfe, but to take only his allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and to lay out to every one according to the mind and will of his Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>We are to relieve the diſtreſſes of our poore brethren, becauſe it is a part of honeſtie, and therefore our dutie, <hi>Provide things honeſt</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>in the ſight of all men,</hi> Rom. 12.17. and Phil. 4.8, 9. <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are true, honeſt, juſt, pure, lovely, of good report, if there be in them any vertue or praiſe we ſhould thinke on ſuch things,</hi> and what no more? <hi>Thoſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which ye have both learned and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and heard and ſeen in me, doe:</hi> we cannot approve our ſelves ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men in the ſight of God; if we be altogether wanting in this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty toward man, for workes of mercy are workes of piety, ſo far forth conſidered as commanded of God, and done in conſcience and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God; if man only call'd for reliefe at our hands, we might be hold excuſed before God, but whenas God requires it, it muſt be done for Gods ſake, conſcience ſtands bound in this caſe, this is one halfe of the royall law,<note n="*" place="margin">Mark 12.31.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> and how doe we love him, if we be hard-hearted towards him? <hi>who ſo hath this worlds good, and ſeeth his brother hath need, and ſhutteth up his bowels of compaſſion from him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qui panperi e cemoſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am dat, Deo ſuavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> odorem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificat. <hi>Cypri.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>how dwelleth the love of God in him?</hi> 1 Joh. 3.17. To give almes is a religious worke, for it is an evangelicall ſacrifice. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16. <hi>To doe good, and to communicate, forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well-pleaſed:</hi> if therefore thou would'ſt pleaſe God, thou muſt ſee that amongſt the reſt of thy ſacrifices, this be not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Hence then may be reproved two ſorts of people, of the which in theſe dayes are moſt men, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:111946:15"/>
            <p>That doe not account it their duty; they think it to be a thing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sort.</hi>
               </note> and not neceſſary, they may doe well in giving reliefe, and they may let it alone, and not doe amiſſe; who ſhall compell them to give away what is their own? even he requires it of thee, to whom thou oweſt thy ſelfe and all thou haſt; they thinke they ought to get and lay up all they can, but doe not account it their dutie as well to lay out, and doe therewithall all the good they can; hence comes it to paſſe that men in this thing are at the beſt ſo indifferent, for they thinke they are free, and not bound hereto by duty, and hence it is that the ſuperfluitie of mens goods, which is the portion of the poore, is laviſht out and waſted in profuſe and vaine expences, yea, in the maintenance of baſe and ſinfull luſts, for by that time pride, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, drunkenneſſe, voluptuouſneſſe, and all manner of exceſſe and riot have had their ſhare, there is ſcarce a farthing left for the poore, nay (it may be) a great deale is ſet on the ſcore, and much more then is their owne ſpent in theſe things; oh that ſuch would but conſider what an account will they be able to give in, that are in ſo great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reares with God, when the judgement is ſet, and the bookes opened,<note place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> wherein all the particular paſſages of their whole life ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewed, and there will it be found, and brought forth againſt them: <hi>Memorandum,</hi> At ſuch a time by ſuch an one were ſo many pounds laid out (coſt needleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) in bravery of apparell, rich attire, and phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall faſhions, and ſo much more at another time, and ſo from time to time the like: whenas ſo many poore creatures at the ſame time had not a good ragge to cover them. <hi>Item,</hi> ſuch vaſt ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney laviſht out without any meaſure in feaſts and banquettings, whenas the poore that were ready to periſh for hunger would have been glad of the ſcraps and fragments, that were given to their hounds and hawkes,<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 16.21.</note> yea, faine would they have been refreſhed with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry crummes that fell from their tables. <hi>Item,</hi> ſuch a treaſure waſted in needleſſe and unneceſſary buildings, ſo many Walkes and Galleries, Turrets and Pyramides, ſuch ſetting up, pulling downe, tranſpoſing, tranſplacing to make gay houſes (which were very mock-beggers) and ſo much yearely caſt away in coſtly furniture, with which their houſes were well-ſtuft and fill'd, whenas multitudes of poore people were driven to wander about, and had no certaine dwelling place, had no other houſe then the wide world, no other bed then the hard ground, and no other canopie then the open Heaven. <hi>Item,</hi> ſo many
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111946:16"/>hundreds ſpent in law-ſuits for the ſatisfying of a ſelfe-will, and as much more in ſports and paſtimes for the pleaſing of a carnall minde, whenas never a poore creature was one penny the better for all this: what anſwer can ſuch make to theſe things, will they not then be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeechleſſe or ſelfe-condemned? if men did but beleeve this that for the want of this duty they ſhould be called to ſo ſtrict an account, one would thinke they would not be ſo wanting therein, but the cauſe is they account it not a dutie.</p>
            <p>That doe not practiſe it as their duty:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sort.</hi>
               </note> they will peradventure in words acknowledge what they ought to doe in this kind, but little or nothing is done, like as many (eſpecially in theſe dayes taking the advantage of the times by reaſon of the preſent obſtruction of juſtice, and meaning to ſhew more knavery then honeſtie) being demanded of thoſe to whom they are endebted ſuch ſummes of money that have been for a long time due, ſtill confeſſe the debt and acknowledge, it hath been a great while due, and more then time it were paid, but put off ſtill with good words from time to time, and indeed means not to pay at all, if they can poſſibly ſhift it, and except they be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; thus deale many people with the poore to whom they owe much, but will part with nothing but faire<note n="*" place="margin">Vox &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea nihil.</note> words at the moſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 49.21.</note> like <hi>Naphtali,</hi> they give good words, as if the poore as<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Ephraim</hi> could be fed with wind; alas poore creatures their caſe is to be pittied, it is fit they ſhould be relieved, the Lord help them, God comfort them, it is a work of charity for good people to do: for them, and many ſuch like ſpeeches, which are the expreſſions onely of a complementall charity,<note place="margin">Luke 16.21.</note> ſuch like <hi>Dives</hi> his dogges, all they can doe is but to licke a poore man with their tongues,<note place="margin">Matt. 17.27.</note> or like <hi>Peters</hi> fiſh that had money in the mouth but not a hand to give it; bare words what are they but wind; and ſuch verball charity what is it but as clouds and wind without raine? it is but of an airy ſubſtance, and hath not the ſolidity ſcarce of a penny weight, for if all the good words &amp; well-wiſhings of ſuch were worth but a two pence or three pence, they would by no meanes part with them, theſe are thoſe exploded by the Apoſtle, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.15, 16. <hi>If a brother or ſiſter be naked, and deſtitute of daily food; And one of you ſay unto them, Depart in peace, be you warmed and filled: in n withſtanding yee give them not thoſe things which are needfull to the body: what doth it profit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> If it be our duty, how carefull, how conſcionable ſhould we be in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111946:16"/>the performance of this our duty? The more to move hereto conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p>God lookes for it to be done,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Motive</hi> 1.</note> we have a word of command to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us to the duty (as was ſhewed in the proofe of the point) and how can we approve our ſelves upright in the ſight of God, unleſſe we have<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.6.</note> reſpect to all his Commandements; he hath made us his Almners, and therefore expects we ſhould</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Give to whom he would have us, <hi>viz.</hi> to the poore, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.11.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As much as he would have us, <hi>viz.</hi> according to that we have, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As often as he would have us, <hi>viz.</hi> when there is need, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In that manner that he would have us, <hi>viz.</hi> for conſcience ſake, in obedience to God, and out of love to our poore brethren.</p>
            <p>God looks upon what is done; God knowes our charity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Motive</hi> 2.</note> and takes eſpeciall notice of our giving to the poore for his ſake,<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>I know thy works</hi> (ſaith Chriſt to his Church in Thyatira) <hi>and charity and ſervice, and faith, and patience,</hi> &amp;c. theſe chiefe things remarkable in her, he is ſaid to know, that is in a ſpeciall manner, with the knowledge of approbation, ſo to know as richly to reward, this he makes knowne that the leaſt thing that is given (though but<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 10.41.</note> 
               <hi>a cup of cold water</hi>) for his ſake, ſhall not be forgotten, and it is obſervable that in that place charitie (that is of the right kind that doth appeare in deed, and is ſeen in ſervice) is<note n="*" place="margin">And the ſame in 1 Theſ. 3.6.</note> joyned with faith; for without this there is no faith, and ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> no pleaſing of God, foraſmuch as faith is dead, and no faith without works, now to releeve the poore is a principall worke of faith, excellent fruit that doth ſpring from a lively faith, without which it cannot profit, all which the Apoſtle doth make to appeare at large, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.14. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as a man may<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.1.</note> beſtow all his goods to feed the poore, and yet want charity, and ſo it may profit him nothing, that we may the better diſcharge our duty herein, let us conſider how, or in what manner it is to be done, for that purpoſe th ſe directions will not be amiſſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give juſtly: <hi>i. e.</hi> of goods rightly got, otherwiſe thou giveſt not that is thine owne to give,<note place="margin">In what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to give Almes: <hi>viz.</hi> 1.</note> and canſt thou thinke to do or to get any good by ſtolne goods? if thou ſcrapeſt together earthly goods by wicked and indirect meanes, and afterwards doſt give out of theſe to the poore, if the curſe doth leave them, yet will it ſtill haunt thee:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111946:17"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>Cast thy bread</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>upon the waters;</hi> let it be thine owne, and not other mens, for that will be no advantage, but every way<note n="*" place="margin">Lucrum ex injuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ittà damaum.</note> loſſe to thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Give wiſely: the good man conſiders<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 41 1. <hi>vet. Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſl.</hi>
               </note> wiſely of the poore, now wiſedome herein muſt be ſeen both in reſpect of the giver, it muſt be according to his ability, as <hi>Act.</hi> 11.29. and of the receivers, it muſt be according to their neceſſity, as <hi>Act.</hi> 4.35.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Give ſincerely: <hi>He that giveth</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8.) <hi>let him doe it with ſimplicitie: i.e.</hi> with ſingleneſſe of heart, looking for no reward at the hands of man, for<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 6.32, 33, 34, 35. <hi>Sunt qui pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us parùm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ribuunt, ut am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> accipiant, quae magis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio eſt quam eleemoſyna.</hi> Hiet. in Ep. Lact. Inſt. lib. 6. cap. 12.</note> 
               <hi>If ye love them which love you</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>what thanke have ye? for ſinners alſo love thoſe that love them. And if ye doe good to them which doe good to you, what thank have ye? for ſinners doe even the ſame. And if ye lend to them of whom ye hope to receive, what thanke have ye? for ſinners alſo lend to ſinners, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as much againe. But love ye your enemies, and doe good, and lend, hoping for nothing againe: and your reward ſhall be great. Tenendum eſt omnimodò ut ab officio miſericordiae ſpes recipiendi abſit omninò.</hi> This muſt be held for certaine, that in the works of mercy there muſt not be ſo much as any hope of requitall, that is, from thoſe to whom we ſhew mercy: we muſt not then be double minded, but ſincere hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that worke.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Give liberally: for Almes muſt be a matter of bounty, and not of covetouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5. it is as ſeed that muſt be ſcattered abroad with a free and full hand, <hi>ver.</hi> 6.9. who ſo bad a husband as to ſow his ground to halves, becauſe he will ſpare his ſeed? what wiſe man will keep in his goods, and let his chiefeſt commedities lie dead by him in his ware-houſe whenas trading is quick, and not rather bring forth ſtill as long as there is any, that ſo by traffique he may at length have a rich returne?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Give willingly: otherwiſe all thou doſt in this kind is nothing worth, be it more or leſſe that thou parteſt with, God looks it ſhould be with heart and good will, or not at all; <hi>Every man according as he purpoſeth in his heart, ſo let him give</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>not grudging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or of neceſſitie: for God loveth a cheerefull giver.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. He gives well that gives willingly, what therefore is wanting in thy hand ſupply with thy heart, though a bargaine is valued by the worth of the thing bought, yet a gift is by the minde of the giver: hence comes it that Almes is not only called <hi>beneficence,</hi> that ſignifies well-doing,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111946:17"/>but alſo a <hi>benevolence</hi> that ſignifies well-willing, for that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done well, that proceeds not from good will.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Give conſcionably: that is, meerely for conſcience fake, chiefly in obedience to God, and out of our duty we owe to him who requires this at our hands; and not for by-ends and baſe reſpects, not out of vain-glory, or for the praiſe of men, for if ſo, we looſe our reward. <hi>Take heed that ye doe not your almes before men to be ſeene of them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non eſt ingrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deo quae viſa fuerit ob homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus eleemoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, ſed quae ideo facta eſt, ut viſa ſit.</note> 
               <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ye have no reward of your Father which is in heaven. Therefore when thou do'ſt thine almes doe not ſound a trumpet before thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.1, 2. ſee more of this in the following verſes: Whereupon <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> in his Comment upon that place ſaies thus, That almes is not rejected of God, that is ſeene of men, but that which is done for that end that it might be ſeene.</p>
            <p>Now that we have underſtood that it is our duty to relieve thoſe that are in want, and in what manner this is to be done. In the laſt place (that we may have no excuſe to ſhift it off) we are to conſider the perſons to be relieved, who thoſe are that we are to ſee to and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for, and this brings in the third point, which is this,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label>
               <hi>We are not to ſuffer any to periſh in extreme need for want of neceſſary reliefe:</hi> So that this grace of charitie ſeemes to be univerſall, it is to be not only in all, but alſo to be extended towards all, it hath an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of a large extent, it will not be ſtraitned in too narrow a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, for it knowes almoſt no bounds, it is not a ſcanty grace, no nor partiall, but free-hearted to any, open-handed to all.</p>
            <p>What all? ſome are rather to be puniſhed then relieved,<note place="margin">Object.</note> ſo altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther undeſerving, that it is no charity at all to do any thing for them,<note place="margin">Qui largiuntur indignis bona, malos roborant materia vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuppeditata. Anſw.</note> and we might be thought rather to offend if we ſhould give any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe to ſuch as are vile and prophane wretches, for what doe we in ſo doing but maintaine them in their vicious courſe of life?</p>
            <p>We are bound to afford helpe or reliefe to all or any, only thus farre, <hi>viz</hi> in theſe two reſpects:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In caſe of extreme neceſſity; if they be ſuch as are altogether diſabled from doing any thing for themſelves, if no way or meanes be left them, but that without help they muſt needs unavoidably pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, then are we bound to doe for them; ſo farre forth as they are ſhiftleſſe and helpleſs of themſelves, we muſt put to our helping hand, in ſuch a caſe we muſt not reſpect the perſon but his condition, <hi>If I have ſeen</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>any periſh for want of clothing, or any poore without
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111946:18"/>covering;</hi> none ſo wicked or wretched, that we may ſuffer to periſh for want of neceſſary reliefe;<note n="*" place="margin">Qui perituro ſuccurrere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, ſi non ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currerit, eum occidit. <hi>Lact. Inſt. li. 6. ca. 11.</hi>
               </note> He that ſees one in extreme need, and may but will not relieve him, is guilty of his death.</p>
            <p>So farre forth as it is a work of mercy: for ſome there are in great need, and yet no deed of charity to relieve them, foraſmuch as they are not impotent but impudent poore, their poverty is voluntary and not neceſſary, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> they are indeed poore, but it is through their owne choice, they are ſuch becauſe they will be ſuch, they wilfully remaine in a needy condition, they have taſted the ſweetneſſe of the ſweat of other mens browes, and therefore they care not ſo long as they know they ſhall be provided for, and they will not doe for themſelves what they may, for they might doe otherwiſe if they would; in ſuch a caſe ſurely (at leaſt ſo farre forth) a man is not bound to relieve them, though they be in ſome great need; concerning ſuch the Apoſtle doth give order which is to be obſerved, <hi>viz. That if any man will not worke, neither ſhould he eat. For we heare</hi> (ſait he) <hi>that there are ſome which walke among you diſorderly, working not at all, but are buſie-bodies. Now them that are ſuch, we command, and exhort by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that with quietneſſe they worke and eat their own bread.</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>So that (theſe things conſidered) it doth appeare that in caſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable neceſſitie, we are (as a work of meer mercy) to afford reliefe to any; and that this is our duty may be proved <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.42. <hi>Give to him that asketh thee: and from him that would borrow of thee, turne not thou away:</hi> it is indefinitely ſpoken, him, whoſoever he be, without exception or exemption, for in ſuch caſes before given, there muſt be no partiality, or reſpect of perſons, and therefore this him S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſhewes to be every man, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 30. and in the ſame ſenſe ſpeakes the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>As we have opportunity, let us doe good unto all men:</hi> that is, ſo farre forth as there is occaſion given, and their need requiring: <hi>Especially unto them who are of the houſhold of faith;</hi> we are indeed to doe moſt for them that are beſt, but yet ſo farre forth as there is neceſſity, we muſt doe good to all, or any; and this our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our doth make plaine to us in his Parable <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.30.37. where the diſtreſſed Jew was relieved by the good Samaritane, who caſually, or occaſionally lighted upon him by the way, and though he was a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, yet in this caſe he accounted him to be his neighbour, whom he was bound to, to doe for; hereby are we given to underſtand, that every one in ſuch a caſe is a mans neighbour, not only his kindred and<note place="margin">* Diſting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt de pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te ſell. vel ex coacta neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, vel ex propriâ volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. <hi>Tho. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:111946:18"/>acquaintance, but whomſoever he hath to doe withall, or that any way ſtands in need of help, in caſe of extremity the very Samaritane muſt help the Jew; Every object of miſery muſt we readily embrace that we meet with to ſhew mercy to, whether it be friend or foe, Jew or Gentile, Chriſtian or Pagan: And to the performance of this duty we are bound in divers reſpects:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> In caſe of humanity; becauſe we are men, and therefore fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creatures, we are all of the ſame fleſh and bloud, and were at firſt made of the ſelfe ſame lump of clay, <hi>He hath made of one blond all rations of men, Act.</hi> 17.26. we are all by creation the children of one and the ſame father, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. and therefore are fellow brethren, and ſhould we not doe then one for another? we ſhould degenerate from men, yea even from the bruit beaſts, if we ſhould not ſhew pitty to thoſe of our owne kind; the irrationall creatures howſoever many times are fierce and furious one kind againſt another, yet, in time of miſery by the dictate of common ſenſe will be helpfull and ſerviceable to thoſe of their own kind; in caſe of extreme neceſſity we are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to relieve the bruit beaſts, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.4. and how much more is one man better then all they? this argument much moved <hi>Job</hi> to ſtoope to the meaneſt of thoſe that did belong to him. He did not deſpiſe the cauſe of his man or maid-ſervant, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. for ſaith he, <hi>Did not he that made me in the wombe, make him? and did not one faſhion us in the wombe?</hi> ver: 15.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In point of equity; becauſe we muſt do as we would be done by; this the golden rule both of Law and Goſpell, given by our Saviour. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.12. this comes cloſe home to the conſcience, and is to all men ſo cleare and convincing, that none can gain-ſay or finde fault with it; and in this particular we muſt conſider the diſtreſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of other men, as if it were our owne, <hi>Remember them that are in bonds as bound with them, and them which ſuffer adverſity, at being your ſelves alſo in the body,</hi> Heb. 13.3. in our ſerious ſad thoughts put our ſelves into their caſe, and our own conſciences cannot but then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us, that if we were in ſuch extremity or neceſſity, we would not that others ſhould deny us reliefe, by reaſon of pay exceptions that might be taken againſt our perſons, but we would have it how ever, and not be ſaid nay, becauſe in extreme need; and if ſo, then by the aforeſaid rule is it our duty to doe for others, as we would be done by our ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:111946:19"/>
            <p>In regard of Gods Example; (which is altogether without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) he is herein impartiall and no reſpecter of perſons, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> for he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributes theſe common good things freely to all, or any, according to the need or neceſſity of his creature as in his wiſdome he ſees beſt, which he chieſly hath reſpect to; herein he dealeth with men moſt commonly according to their needineſſe, and not alwaies according to their goodneſſe, hereby reaching us to doe the like, therefore is this his example propounded for our imitation, we muſt ſhew our ſelves herein to be the children of God, in being like our heavenly Father, who doth good to all, even to his enemies, he cauſeth the ſunne to ſhine, and the raine to fall upon the evill as well as the good, and the unjuſt as well as the juſt; and if we now ſhew favour only to thoſe of our owne kin, what ſingular thing doe we? but if to any in caſe of neceſſity, then do we attaine to a higher degree in well-doing then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o others; and it muſt be our emulation to endeavour the perfection of goodneſſe in all things, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.45-48.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In reſpect of Gods Image, ſome part of which is to be ſeen in all mankind,<note place="margin">Peſſimus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num habet um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras quaſdam ceu veſtigia quaedam crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris.</note> even in the worſt of men, though much ruinated and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, yet is it not wholly extinguiſhed or extirpated, every man as a man ſets forth the handy-work of God, and therefore in this regard favour is to be afforded to every one, if not for the mans ſake, yet for Gods ſake whoſe creature he is, and whoſe image he beares; the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of a King (though but rudely ſet forth) is to be reſpected in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the perſon whom it repreſents, and the baſe uſage of it (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if through contempt) reflects upon the perſon, and tends to the diſhonour of him whoſe picture it is; ſo<note n="*" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.20.</note> 
               <hi>If any man ſay I love God, and hateth his brother, he is alyar: for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen? q.d.</hi> as we deal with men in this kind, the Lord accounts as done to him, foraſmuch as man as made of God is the viſible image of the inviſible God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Hence then are to be reproved thoſe that when they are call'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for reliefe (when they have nothing elſe where withall to excuſe themſelves) will cavill and except againſt the perſons to be relieved, if they can but pick any hole or find any fault, or can ſay any thing (be it true or falſe) againſt thoſe that want reliefe, they are glad if they can any way ſpare their purſe, and think all they ſave this way is clear gain, wonderfull it is to ſee, with what vaine ſhifts and frivolous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes many in theſe dayes do ſtop poore mens mouthes. The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111946:19"/>tels us of <hi>Autigonus</hi> whom he not without cauſe doth brand with infamy for his cavelling with a Cynike,<note place="margin">Seneca de Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiis lib. 2. cap. 17.</note> who asked of the King a talent, his anſwer was, that it was too much for a Cynike to receive; then he begged a penny, that (ſaith he) is too little for me a King to give<note n="*" place="margin">Turpiſſima eſt ejuſmodi ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villatio, invenit quo modo neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum daret, in denario regem, in denarioregem, in talento Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum reſpexit: cum poſſit &amp; denarium tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Cynico dare, &amp; talen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tanquam rex. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> thus he found an excuſe for both, and ſo by that meanes gave him nothing at all; ſuch like ſhifts do men make, and ſtrain their wits to find out many more to keep back in their owne hands that, that might benefit the poore; well, though men may be thus put off, yet God will not be ſo dallied with, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7. know and conſider well that God requires of thee to give reliefe in extreme need to any, look to it then as thou wilt anſwer the contrary at thy perill, it lies upon thee as a duty, how canſt thou then be diſcharged?</p>
            <p>Let us learne well that which we of our ſelves are not ſo willing as we ſhould be to practiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> without any evaſion or protraction free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embrace every object and occaſion for the doing of good, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> away with theſe needleſſe <hi>quaries,</hi> where? or who? when? or what? how? or why? for whereſoever he be, or whoſoever he is, that whenſoever ſtands in need of whatſoever help we can afford, we muſt howſoever ſee that he doth not miſcarry through our default or neglect, and why? becauſe it is our duty, which (all excuſes ſet apart) we muſt look to, <hi>viz.</hi> not to ſuffer any to periſh for want of clothing, or any poore to be without covering, we may not then in this thing ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect any mans perſon as his<note n="*" place="margin">Sive ille ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, ſive cogna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſit, &amp; affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, nihil in illo aliud conſideres niſi pauperta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: ſine diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione omnibus indigentibus ſimplicitèr tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buamus non quaerentes cui, ſed quare demus. <hi>Hier. in Ep.</hi>
               </note> condition, for charity is to look direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the caſe and collaterally into the cauſe; not ſolely the worth, but chiefly the want of the perſon is to be regarded.</p>
            <p>But ſuch are ſtrangers to me, I know not whence they come, nor whither they go, I never ſaw their faces before, and I know not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what they be, nor whether I ſhould relieve them or no?<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>Such an one ſpeakes like <hi>Nahal,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.10, 11. who proved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a fool, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. but hear what God ſaith,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
               <hi>And if thy brother be waxen poore, and fallen in decay with thee, then thou ſhalt relieve him, yea, though he be a ſtranger, or a ſojourner, that he may live with thee,</hi> Levit. 25.35.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Such are unthankfull, and never contented, the more one does for them, the more ingratefull they prove?</p>
            <p>The Ingratitude of the poore indeed doth oft-times much coole the charity of the rich, but let not that diſcourage thee,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> foraſmuch as thou haſt a better pay-maſter, who will ſee that thou ſhalt not be the looſer; and<note n="*" place="margin">Ingratus eſt. non mibi fecit injuriam, ſed ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi, nec ideò pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>griut dabo, ſed diligentius, <hi>Sen. de ben. lib. 7. cap. 32.</hi>
               </note> this is their fault and not thine, let not therefore their ſin
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111946:20"/>of ingratitude cauſe thee to ſin in the not diſcharging of thy dutie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the waters</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 11.1.) <hi>for thou ſhalt find it after many dayes: q.d.</hi> though that thou giveſt to the poore may ſeeme to be coſt caſt away, eſpecially if it fall into the hands of ingratefull perſons, ſo that thou think'ſt never to have any thing againe, not ſo much as thanks, no not one good word for all that thou doſt, yet ſpare not ever the more; for it is as a venture at ſea that ſhall certainly come home at laſt with a rich prize, when as thou doſt little expect it, but had'ſt quite given it over as loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> Such are mine utter enemies, that have done me all the miſchiefe that poſſibly they could, and I will ſerve them in the ſame kind, ſhall I doe any thing for them? no ſurely they ſhall lie and ſtarve, or rot firſt before they ſhall be a penny the better for me, what mine che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? if they might want and periſh I ſhould not be ſorry, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As thou art a Chriſtian,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> let not ſuch curſed ſpeeches proceed out of thy mouth;<note place="margin">Jam. 3.9, 10.</note> know that thou muſt not be wanting in this duty, no nor in any office of love, no not toward thy enemies, as they are thy enemies and have wronged thee; I confeſſe they are otherwiſe to be conſidered as they are Gods enemies, and have diſhonoured him, ſo maiſt thou indeed<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 139.21, 22.</note> hate them, (but it muſt be then as God doth, <hi>viz.</hi> pitty them in reſpect of their perſons, though abhorre them in regard of their ſins) but conſidering them as enemies to us, we may not faile nor fall ſhort in duty towards them; proved,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> By precept: <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.43, 44. the Phariſees by their falſe gloſſe had corrupted Gods law, as in many other things ſo in this, their rule was this, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour, and hate thine enemy</hi> (this was pleaſing enough to corrupt nature,) they underſtood by neighbour in the law to be meant only their friends and acquaintance; <hi>But I ſay unto you</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>q.d.</hi> I muſt learne you another leſſon, <hi>viz. Love your enemies, bleſſe them that cauſe you, doe good to them that hate you, and pray for them which despitefully uſe you, and perſecute you;</hi> ſee, here is love, and offices of love required of us towards our very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, both concerning their ſpirituall as alſo their outward good. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.14.20. <hi>Recompence to no man evill for evill, but if thine, enemy hunger,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Per cibum &amp; potum, omnia bumanitatis efficia intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda.</note> 
               <hi>feed him; if he thirſt, give him</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Carbones ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis coacervabis in caput ejus] <hi>i.e.</hi> animus fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getur in utra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> partem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> aut ex ardore cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titatis beneficili emollietur, aut uretur teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio conſcientia. <hi>Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>drinke, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſo doing,</hi> * <hi>thou ſhalt he ape coales of fire on his head; be not overcome with evill, but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come evill with good. q.d.</hi> doe not as thou art dealt with, but as thou wouldſt be done by, doe not with-hold thy hand from doing: what
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111946:20"/>thou canſt, for (and not againſt) thy enemies,<note place="margin">Poenas ejus in diem judicii cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulabis, <hi>Orig.</hi>
               </note> for thereby thou ſhalt ſo enflame them with thy love, that it ſhall kindle in them burning charity towards thee, or if they continue ſtill in their malice, they ſhal be ſet on fire with the coales of their own conſcience, and of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine juſtice, if therefore thou doſt repay thy enemy evill for evill, thou doſt bring a greater evill upon thy ſelfe; for that was the evill of puniſhment, but thine is the evill of ſin; but if with thy well-doing thou doſt over-match the evill that thy enemy hath done thee,<note place="margin">Is laude d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnus qui malis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocatus reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit bona. <hi>Id.</hi>
               </note> how great a victory doſt thou obtaine? it is a noble thing to overcome, but more noble to overcome evill, but moſt of all to overcome evill with good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By example: wonderfull was the infinite love of God towards us his enemies, in that he received us into his favour, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on us his ſon, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. who is more then if he had given us all things beſide; what could he poſſibly have done more for us? Herein is love indeed, not that we loved God (for we being his utter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, hated him, and were hated of him,) but that he loved us, and ſent his ſon to be the propitiation for our ſins. Beloved, if God ſo loved us, we ought alſo to love one another (for there is an infinite diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and us, and therefore is the enmity farre greater betweene God and us, then is, or poſſibly can be, betweene one and another.) 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.10, 11.</p>
            <p>Another example of this kind we have, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 6.21, 22, 23. the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians (enemies to Gods people) came in an hoſtile manner, and with a malicious minde againſt the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> but were ſtrangely not only diſappointed of their purpoſe, but alſo captivated themſelves, the King of Iſrael ſeeing his enemies to ſtand at his mercy would have ſhewed them no mercy, but cals out to ſlay them; the Prophet is of another minde, and requires them not to be deſtroyed, but to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and then diſmiſſed, which being done, their hearts were ſo mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herewith, that they were thereby ſubdued and overcome for a long while after: many more examples I might produce (were it as needfull as eaſie) even of heathen men and infidels voide of true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace (whoſe excellency hath conſiſted in meere morality) yet by the power of reſtraining grace<note n="*" place="margin">Emollit mores, nes ſinit eſſe ſeros.</note> (which doth mollifie in great part mans curſed cruell nature) have beene eminent and men of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown for their courteſie and bounty towards their greateſt and moſt malicious enemies; oh how inexcuſable ſhall we be, if ſuch as theſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111946:21"/>ſhall riſe up in judgement, and for this thing amongſt other things condemne many of thoſe that profeſſe themſelves Chriſtians? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that to relieve our very enemies, and that (in caſe of neceſſity) as if they were our very friends is a hard ſaying (that is, to thoſe in whom is nothing better then corrupt nature) and who can heare it? but is there any to be found that practice it? oh it is ſo harſh a thing that fleſh and bloud cannot beare nor brooke it, and no wonder, for (the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>Fleſh and bloud cannot inherit the Kingdome of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50. a naturall man, yea, the beſt of men (as touching the part unregenerate) cannot poſſibly ſubmit to this, it muſt be pure grace that muſt yeeld hereunto, <hi>for the carnall mind is enmity againſt God, and is not ſubject to the law of God, nor indeed can be.</hi> Rom. 8.7.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> Such are vile and wicked wretches, that deſerve not any thing, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it is they ſhould be ſuffered, or have any thing at all given them, and what ſhould I relieve theſe?</p>
            <p>Herein muſt wiſdome be ſeene,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> we muſt ſo give even to the worſt of men, that they periſh not for want of reliefe, and yet withall make it to appeare, that we doe not countenance nor will maintaine them in their ſin; we muſt ſupport humane nature even in a wicked man;<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſt otelet reprehen ſus à quodam, quòd eleem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſynam dediſset impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, Non homini (inquit) dedi, ſed humanae for. ti. <hi>Laert. lib. 5. cap. 1.</hi>
               </note> ſo the Philoſopher excuſed himſelfe ſaying, he conſidered not the man, but mankind.</p>
            <p>Again, we muſt not look altogether to the deſerts of the party, for conſider, if God ſhould deale with us according to our deſerts, what could we expect at his hands? <hi>I am not worthy</hi> (ſaith that holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch) <hi>of the leaſt of all the mercies, and all the truth, which thou haſt ſhewed unto thy ſervant. Gen.</hi> 32.10. God indeed feeds us to the full with the fineſt of the wheat, with honey out of the rock, and with the pure bloud of the grape,<note place="margin">Deu. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13, 14. Pſal. 81.16.</note> but we are ſuch altogether undeſerving creatures, as unworthy we are of the very refuſe, or crummes that fall from us.</p>
            <p>I have given already to many, and cannot to every one, it will not hold out, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>5</label> what muſt we ever be giving, and never give over? I have done well for ſuch and ſuch, and there cannot be any more expected of me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Give a portion to ſeven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
               <hi>and alſo to eight, for thou knoweſt not what evill ſhall be upon the earth: Eccleſ.</hi> 11.2.<note n="*" place="margin">Quod aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do de neceſſitate amittendum eſt, ſpontè pro divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ remunerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one diſtribuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt. <hi>Cyp. ſer. de tleemoſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>q. d.</hi> thou knoweſt not how God may deal with thee, or what thou haſt, therefore whilſt thou art, and whilſt thou haſt, be ſtill doing good therewith, and that not to a few, but let many, yea any have a part and ſhare therein, obſerving the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111946:21"/>cautions before given, having reſpect both to thy abilitie, and their neceſſitie: See <hi>page</hi> 25, 26.</p>
            <p>Theſe are, though not all, yet moſt of the chiefe of thoſe many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes that men make, to ſhift off their duty in this particular; which (we ſee) nevertheleſſe will not hold them excuſed before God; other objections of leſſe note are not worth the anſwering.</p>
            <p>What now remaines? but that knowing theſe things,<note place="margin">Joh. 13.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> we ſhould accordingly doe them, for the knowledge of duty without practice availes nothing, be alwayes therefore doing good in this kind to one or other, and for encouragement in this well-doing, ſet before you the rich recompence of reward; conſider what the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.8, 9, 10. <hi>God is able to make all grace abound toward you, that ye alwayes having ſufficiencie in all things may abgund to every good work (as it is written, He hath disperſed abroad, he hath given to the poore, his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe remaineth for ever.) Now he that miniſtreth ſeed to the ſower. both miniſter bread for your food, and multiply your ſeed ſowen, and increaſe the fruits of your righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> From the generall, let us deſcend to a particular; If in caſe of inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table neceſſity, we are to afford reliefe to any, what thinke you then (brethren) of the poore Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland?</hi> Oh let us conſider their diſtreſſe, and let us take notice of our duty, though our eyes have not ſeen, yet our eares have heard, and that at large; time after time how ill it fares with them; nay have not we our ſelves been eye-witneſſes in great part of their miſerie? how many of them in all this time have come to our doores, and preſented themſelves before us as viſible ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of our pittie? let us not turne away our faces, cloſe out eies, ſtop our eares, and harden our hearts againſt them;<note place="margin">Fronte capilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ pòſt eſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio calva.</note> 
               <hi>As we have opportunitie</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>let us doe good,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. advantages of times, and opportunities of doing good we muſt catch hold of, and not let ſlip; and now have we an opportunity put into our hands, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting but a heart, their diſtreſſes are powerfull ſutors, which do cry day and night, and not give us reſt, how then can we poſſibly give them the deniall? The high Court of Parliament in their late<note n="*" place="margin">This was preached upon the occaſion of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for the reliefe of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> then ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come out, &amp; required by Miniſters in all places to be commended to the people.</note> Declaration and Ordinance do lively preſent their gaſping conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto us, (whoſe ſpirit is not moved, whoſe heart not wounded, whoſe ſoul not afflicted?) and in their behalfe do ſecond their ſute, and call upon us for a charitable ſupply of the very neceſſaries of life for them: if then we now ſit ſtill, and do nothing, how inexcuſable ſhall we be? tremble to think that any of us ſhould ſuffer any of them to periſh for want of clothing, or to remaine ſo poor that they ſhould be without covering.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:111946:22"/>
            <p>They are none of our kindred and acquaintance, farre from us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to us, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> therefore are we not bound to doe for them.</p>
            <p>Are they not men,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and are they not in need? then are we bound more to them then to others that are in leſſe need, though neerer to us; nay, but further, are they not of near a kin to us? are they (not <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Proteſtants, and ſo of the ſame fleſh and bloud with us? yea, as we profeſſe our ſelves Chriſtians, ſo are not they the ſame (ſuch as have been brought to his miſerable condition for the true Religions ſake) and therefore are we brethren, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8. and ſhould not ſuch do one for another? 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. as alſo fellow members, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. and ſo ought to have a ſympathizing diſpoſition, <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 26. remember what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Let us doe good to all men, but eſpecially to them who are of the houſhold of faith;</hi> which is the multitude of all true beleevers, diſperſed throughout the whole earth, known by the name of the Church Militant, which is called Gods Family or houſhold, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.19. now, eſpeciall and more then ordinary care muſt be had of ſuch as theſe that are in want, whenſoever we heare thereof, and any opportunity ſeem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for that purpoſe we muſt afford reliefe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> But we feare the ſucceſt, the ſupplies formerly ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t-have (as we have heard) oft-times miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tried, and now may againe fall into their enemies hands, and ſo do more hurt then good.</p>
            <p>All future events of things are uncertain &amp; unknown to us,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> we muſt diſcharge our duty,<note place="margin">Omnla etentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra jacent in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certo.</note> and leave the ſucceſſe to God, we muſt uſe the means, and then refer all to the good bleſſing of God; how know we, but that hereby the Lord trieth us; whether we will truſt him or no?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> We muſt provide for our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And what ſhall we be altogether and only for our ſelves?<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> never was it merry world, ſince ſo much ſelfe-love ſhewed it ſelfe in the world; the Apoſtle gives us another leſſon which we muſt learn, <hi>viz. Let no man-ſeek his own</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> not only his own) <hi>but every man anothers wealth</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> as well as his own) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.24. (cleane contrary to the Maxime of worldlings, which is, <hi>Every one ſhift for himſelfe</hi>) and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this kind we have <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Looke not every man on his owne things, but every man alſo on the things of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> I have done well already for my part, I gave a great deale before for their reliefe, and therefore may well be excuſed now?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the morning ſow thy ſeed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
               <hi>and in the evening withhold not thy hands for thou knoweſt not whether ſhall proſper, either this or that, or whether they both ſhall be alike good, Eccleſ.</hi> 11.6. it may be, thou art yet to receive the bleſſing for what thou haſt formerly done, or peradventure, now
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111946:22"/>thou maiſt expect a greater bleſſing then before; or what if now to reape the fruit of all? do not therefore ſlack thy hand, <hi>For whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reape. Let us not then be Weary in Well-doinge for in due ſeaſon we ſhall reape, if we faint not.</hi> Gal. 6.7, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>5</label> Theſe are hard times, vaſt expences, great charges and heavie taxes are laid upon us, we are daily call'd upon to disburſe for one thing or other, ſo that we know not what to doe, nor how to live.</p>
            <p>There is a time for all things, a time to lay up, and time to lay out,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> theſe are not gathering but ſpending times, this is not a time to hoard up, but we muſt now bring forth out of our ſtore-houſe all things both old and new: conſider what the Lord ſaith to <hi>Baruch</hi> by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Chap. 45.4, 5. <hi>The Lord ſaith thus, Behold, that which I have built, I will breake downe, and that which I have planted, I will plucke up, even this whole land. And ſeekeſt thou great things for thy ſelfe? ſeeke them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>6</label> I am not able, alas I have not wherewithall; I would, but I cannot.</p>
            <p>Take we heed we doe not diſable our ſelves; true,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> neither God nor man require of us impoſſibilities, to do in this kind above that we are able (yet let me tell you upon extraordinary occaſions we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine our ſelves though ſomething above our ordinary ability, as did thoſe Chriſtians whom the Apoſtle applauds 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3.) but God and our own conſcience knows beſt, whether this be a reall truth or only a fained excuſe; it is to be feared, moſt want nothing but a willing mind; <hi>For if there be firſt a willing minde, it is accepted according to that a man hath and not according to that he hath not.</hi> 2 Cor. 8.12. the widows two mites (where there is nothing, or but little) willingly parted with, is more acceptable to God, then all that worldly rich men give out of their abundance, <hi>Mark</hi> 12.42, 43, 44. what can more be ſaid even by thoſe that deſire to cavill, or what can more be ſpoken to ſtop the mouthes of ſuch? I end with a motive or two, which may move our hearts to put to our helping hands to relieve the wants of diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Ireland. viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How know we but it may be a means to move the Lord to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civull to this land? ſee what he hath promiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Motive</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.10, 11, 12. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, if we caſt off all pitty towards them, we may not look that the Lord ſhould have any compaſſion on us (for nothing is more juſt with God then to pay ſinners home in their<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>c. g. Dives</hi> would not give <hi>Lazarus</hi> a crumme of bread, therfore was himſelfe denied a drop of water.</note> own kind) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109 9.12.16. <hi>Amos</hi> 6.6, 7, 8. ſee there how the Lord threatens thoſe that have not a fellow-feeling of the miſeries of their fellow-brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If the Lord provide for them, and not by our meanes, if we draw
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111946:23"/>back our hand, and follow not cloſe the worke to help forward their deliverance as well as our own, but that the Lord ſhould (through out default) be pleaſed to take ſome other courſe, and bring it about ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, it will not be for our honour, but to our ſhame; as <hi>Mord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> tels <hi>Eſter,</hi> when the people of God were in ſtraits, and ſhe at firſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med loth to put forth her ſelfe, <hi>If thou altogether holdeſt thy peace at this time, then ſhall there enlargement and deliverance ariſe to the Jewes from another place, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ou and thy fathers houſe ſhall be destroyed: And who knoweth, whether thou art come to the kingdome for ſuch a time as this?</hi> Chap. 4.14. ſo, If we altogether hold our hands at this time, there ſhall at length come deliverance to Gods people ſome other way, whenas we and ours may periſh, and who knowes, but that we may be the kingdome that the Lord will hereby try at this time, &amp; in this thing? Set before you the rich recompence of reward: conſider two things, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There will be nothing hereby loſt; for whatſoever in this kind thou parteſt with (be it more or leſſe) it is but a loane lent to the Lord, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſider. </seg>1</label>
               <hi>He that hath pitty on the poore</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Faeneratur Domino. &amp;c. al verbii adum <hi>Orig.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>lendeth</hi> (on uſury) <hi>to the Lord, and that which he hath given, will he pay him again,</hi> Pro. 19.17. and who may we better truſt then God, and what better ſecurity can we deſire then his word? it is the abſolute beſt courſe that uſurers can poſſibly take, to make the moſt and beſt improvement of their money, thus to put it out to Gods uſe (oh that they had but faith to beleeve it) for he is ſo rich a pay-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that the very intereſt ſhalbe far greater then the principall, and ſo ſure a pay-maſter, that he will ſee thou ſhalt be ſure not to want, <hi>He that giveth unto the poore, ſhall not lacke,</hi> Prov. 28.27.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſider. </seg>2</label> Hereby ſhall we receive great gain; If thou giveſt out good meaſure and preſſed down, the Lord will ſee that the return ſhall be made thee ſhaken together and running over. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.38. this (me thinks) ſhould whet on thoſe that are greedy of gain. Alms is fitly compared to ſeed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. and why? becauſe it yeelds a great encreaſe; now there is no man when he ſowes his ground thinks that it is loſt and caſt away, ſo buried in the earth that he ſhall never ſee it more, no, he lookes that that ſhould bring him a great deale more, and pay him with over plus for all his coſt, and this hope makes him prodigall of his ſeed, he freely ſcatters it abroad with a full and open hand, he will ſee that his land ſhall not want ſeed, it ſhall have as much (by his good will) as the ground can bear or bring forth, and what ſhall we be ſuch Atheiſts as to truſt the ground and not God? Fear not, but if we throw out good ſtore of this ſeed, it will yeild us a rich crop (a hundred fold) at harveſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111946:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
